<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pacquet of popish delusions, false miracles, and lying wonders together with many grand divisions among papists: far exceeding both in quality and quantity those among Protestants: notwithstanding their seeming unity. Exposed to the shame of popery. Whereunto is added the papists dissentions from the Protestant: with (that, the enemy so much glorys-in, viz.) the differences of the Protestants among themselves. And, a fearful caution to apostatizing Protestants. By Mercurius Hibernicus.</title>
            <author>Mercurius, Hibernicus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P158A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54401)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2051:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pacquet of popish delusions, false miracles, and lying wonders together with many grand divisions among papists: far exceeding both in quality and quantity those among Protestants: notwithstanding their seeming unity. Exposed to the shame of popery. Whereunto is added the papists dissentions from the Protestant: with (that, the enemy so much glorys-in, viz.) the differences of the Protestants among themselves. And, a fearful caution to apostatizing Protestants. By Mercurius Hibernicus.</title>
                  <author>Mercurius, Hibernicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 61, [1], p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Dawks,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Half-title reads "Popish delusions, and divisions." with the words "delusions, and divisions." bracketed together.</note>
                  <note>The last 4 pages are numbered: 57, 70, [indecipherable], [blank].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages cropped with loss of numbering.</note>
                  <note>Errata at the foot of E2r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PACQUET OF Popish Deluſions, Falſe Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and Lying Wonders: Together with Many Grand DIVISIONS Among PAPISTS: Far exceeding both in Quality and Quantity thoſe among Proteſtants: notwithſtanding their ſeeming Unity. Expoſed to the Shame of POPERY.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added The Papiſts DISSENTIONS From the PROTESTANT: With (<hi>That, the <hi>Enemy</hi> ſo much glorys-in,</hi> viz.)</p>
            <p>The Differences of the PROTESTANTS among themſelves.</p>
            <p>And, a fearful Caution to Apoſtatizing Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> MERCURIUS HIBERNICUS.</p>
            <q>Sero, ſed Serio.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Dawks.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:2"/>
            <p>Popiſh DELUSIONS, and DIVISIONS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> This counterfeit deluding Devil (ſeemingly afraid of the Papiſts Holy water) is the true Repreſentative of all ſuch as place a Holineſs where GOD has put none. <hi>See Deluſion</hi> XX.
<hi>pag.</hi> 20.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>A Proceſſion.</head>
               <q>My name <hi>is</hi> Legion, for we are many.
<bibl>Mar. 5 9</bibl>
               </q>
               <figDesc>a winged and horned devil is chased by Roman Catholic priests with holy water, a canopy, crosses and a banner.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The Collier (ſpoken of by Cardinal <hi>Hoſius</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, and ſpeaks the very Dialect of all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Proteſtants as well as Papiſts, who are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchd in their Lives &amp; Converſation, as well Women as Men, that drink, ſwear, forſwear, curſe, whore, &amp;
<hi>c.</hi> But as to an Eternal welfare of their ſouls are idle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, indifferent, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ignorant; fit to be deluded by a blind, ſottiſh Prieſt; thinking it enough to ſay, <hi>They believe as the Church believe,</hi> or, words to that effect. <hi>See the Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <sp>
                  <p>How dost thou believ?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>I believ as t. Church believs.</p>
               </sp>
               <figDesc>a winged and horned devil talks with a man.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:4"/>
            <head>TO <hi>The Right Honourable Sir</hi> ROBERT CLAYTON, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Lord Mayor OF LONDON: AND, One of Its Repreſentatives in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Parliament.</head>
            <p>AS Clouds are diſpell'd, when the <hi>Sun</hi> mounteth in its Vertical Lustre and <hi>Glory:</hi> ſo the noiſom Mists of Vices, and
<hi>vicious Varlets</hi> are diſſipated, as well by the bright beams of
<pb facs="tcp:36213:5"/> 
               <hi>Virtue,</hi> ſhining forth in the Lives and Manners of
<hi>Good Magiſtrates,</hi> (ſuch I take your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and ſome others to be) as by the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> it ſelf; which, as you well know, <hi>is not to be born in vain,</hi> but to be uſed with Legal and Regular <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity</hi> against Offenders, eſpecially incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Ones. Now, What, or Who greater Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders and Delinquents, nay, Who can be reputed more <hi>deſtructive &amp; pernicious</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to any
<hi>Proteſtant State</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> than <hi>Blood-thirſty, murdering, City<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burning, All-deſtroying, plotting Papiſts?</hi> What can we term the whole Rout of their <hi>Clergy?</hi> eſpecially their
<hi>Jeſuits</hi> (thoſe <hi>Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Furies</hi>) leſs than the
<hi>Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Mankind!</hi> for as much as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to prey upon all of their own kind, that are not of their <hi>Execrable</hi> Religion! which yet, neither the Fiercest <hi>Lyons,</hi> Cruellest <hi>Tygers,</hi> Savage
<hi>Bears,</hi> nor Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb facs="tcp:36213:5"/> 
               <hi>Wolves</hi> were ever guilty of: for theſe <hi>State-Mountebanks</hi> are never idle, but alwayes in action, and perpetual Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to perpetrate the greatest <hi>Villanies</hi> and
<hi>Miſchiefs</hi> imaginable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> your <hi>Care, Diligence</hi> and
<hi>Vigilance,</hi> concerning ſuch Perſons and Things, together with your prudent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> in matters of great Importance (by which we injoy
<hi>good Order</hi> and <hi>Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>) muſt needs be very acceptable to all <hi>good People,</hi> as indeed they are, and will make you, deſervedly, famous to <hi>Poſterity:</hi> And it is hoped, that your
<hi>good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> may raiſe in your <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> a
<hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> and <hi>candid Emulation,</hi> to tread the ſame <hi>Paths of Honour, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> by your Lordſhip ſo regularly <hi>trackt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> for them. I ſay, <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that true Child of <hi>Virtue,</hi> that <hi>Stay</hi> and <hi>Staff</hi> of
<hi>Peace,</hi> that <hi>great Maintainer</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi> for, as
<hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:6"/> ſine prudentia plurimum poterit,</hi> ſo, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Juſtitia nihil valebit Prudentia:</hi> A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<hi>Apothegm,</hi> of thrice worthy <hi>Cicero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> If my Fancy deceive not my Judgment, I know not to whom I ſhould with more <hi>Reaſon</hi> make a ſpecial
<hi>Dedication</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Book</hi> as this, and at ſuch a
<hi>Juncture</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> than to the <hi>Prime Optimate</hi> of the
<hi>Primeſt Proteſtant CITY</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> as <hi>LONDON</hi> is, and is acknowledged ſo to be, even by its moſt <hi>implacable, irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable, reſtleſs, ſworn</hi> and <hi>inſtructed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> who <hi>gnaſh</hi> their Teeth, yea, <hi>pine away</hi> through mere
<hi>Madneſs</hi> and <hi>Malice;</hi> not only to behold ſuch a glorious
<hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from the <hi>Womb</hi> of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and late vaſt Heaps of her own <hi>Rubbiſh &amp; Ruins,</hi> but alſo the
<hi>Detection</hi> of their <hi>(Still Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued) PLOTS;</hi> wherein the great <hi>GOD</hi> is chiefly to be aſpected and <hi>magnified!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:36213:6"/>The Several <hi>Popiſh Deluſions</hi> and
<hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions,</hi> diſplayed in this little Book are not vulgarly known, I am certain; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I preſume, will be the more welcome to the
<hi>Ignorant:</hi> which, though they will be no News to Your
<hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and others: yet, I humbly crave your <hi>Acceptance,</hi> and <hi>Patronage</hi> of this <hi>Work:</hi> Which, I know, will find more
<hi>Enemies</hi> than there are <hi>Words</hi> in it, as ſhall my ſelf, for expoſing it, who <hi>cordially</hi> wiſh all <hi>Health, Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, Safety</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> to your <hi>Self, City</hi> and
<hi>(Proteſtant) Citizens:</hi> to whoſe <hi>Service</hi> and
<hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe,</hi> I have with the ſame
<hi>Ardency</hi> wholly devoted my best <hi>Endeavours,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 23: 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Mercurius Hibernicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:7"/>
            <lg>
               <head>To all Reſolv'd Protestants.</head>
               <l>HELL is broke looſe, the Devil a Hunting rides,</l>
               <l>With Troops of Jeſ'its, and great DONS beſides,</l>
               <l>To Proſelite more Proteſtants; thereby</l>
               <l>The reſt to overthrow more eaſily:</l>
               <l>New Projects are on Foot, and one is this,</l>
               <l>(Whereof they have great Hopes they ſhall not miſs)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> To ſtir up the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> againſt thoſe</l>
               <l>They <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> call: yea, unto Blows;</l>
               <l>Which, God avert. I ſay, <hi>Rome</hi>'s ſtill at work,</l>
               <l>Her num'rous Agents, ſtill among us lurk,</l>
               <l>You know for what. 'Tis time then to be wiſe,</l>
               <l>And learn who Friends are, and who Enemies:</l>
               <l>And that, among your neareſt Neighbours too,</l>
               <l>For ſuch, if Papiſts, can moſt Miſchief you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I have been threatned often with Deſtruction,</l>
               <l>By Prieſts, and Kindred too, for my Religion,</l>
               <l>Yea, peſecuted at Ten years of Age,</l>
               <l>At laſt was forc'd to fly, to ſhun their Rage.</l>
               <l>Again, in Seventy one, and Two and Three,</l>
               <l>Some ſaid, In Time, They'd take a Courſe with me:</l>
               <l>But all their Threats (even ſince I was at School)</l>
               <l>Could never quench my Zeal, nor Courage Cool</l>
               <l>To the Proteſtant Cauſe: Therefore, my Friends,</l>
               <l>I hope you'l own me in ſuch Noble Ends.</l>
               <l>Yet, let me ſay, Though I am ſtill obſcure,</l>
               <l>My Heart's on fire to burn the Romiſh WHORE.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:8"/>'Bove all, to keep her from the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Strand:</l>
               <l>And Cruſh her PIMPS already in the Land.</l>
               <l>Courage in dreadful Times is rarely found,</l>
               <l>I hope moſt of you with it do abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſhall you ſee, ROME'S dark <hi>Idolatry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Image-VVorſhip laid before your Eye.</l>
               <l>In Reading which, you cannot chooſe but Smile,</l>
               <l>Altho the POPE himſelf ſtood-by the while.</l>
               <l>Here Papiſt againſt Papiſt ſhall you ſee,</l>
               <l>And 'mongſt themſelves divided worſe than we,</l>
               <l>For all their ſeeming Uniformity,</l>
               <l>Which, yet, they'r forc'd to, by <hi>Rome's</hi> TYRANNY.</l>
               <l>Accept this little Book, 'till others do</l>
               <l>More lively paint their <hi>Mawmmetry</hi> to you.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mercurius Hibernicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:8"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>HAving lately ſeen a printed Paper concerning a pretended Miracle, wrought by the Power of Almighty God (as the blaſphemous, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly impudent Authors thereof affirm in Print) on the Saint of St.
<hi>Omers, Edmund Gennings!</hi> in the daies of O. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> The reading whereof, brought to my Remembrance, that I had tranſcribed ſeveral ſuch like <hi>Tales, Falſe Miracles,</hi> and <hi>Lying Wonders,</hi> out of an old Book in <hi>Kent,</hi> only for Diverſion ſake: Being in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo ridiculous, ſo abſurd and impoſſible: (yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved for Undoubted Truths by the blind Papiſts) and therefore, think it not unſeaſonable, at this time, to preſent them to publick View, very few of them being known to moſt men: Not doubting, but the ſimpleſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, as well as the intelligent, will not only laugh at them, but utterly ſcorn and deteſt them, and the, now, Promoters of them, as meer Cheats, Juggles, and Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; by which they may ſee and judge, how miſerable not only <hi>Kent,</hi> (for what I have writ, is only of ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in that one County) but other Shires and Counties of <hi>England,</hi> were deluded by the fly Inventions, Magick <pb facs="tcp:36213:9"/> Arts and Impoſtures of the JESUITES, Prieſts, Monks, Fryers, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> whilſt POPERY reigned here, to the great Diſhonor of GOD, and the Woful Seduction, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Eternal Deſtruction of Milions of credulous Papiſts, with whom, even to this very day, the words and perſwaſions of one blind Prieſt, was and is of more Force and Authority than the whole Scriptures. For, they are bound, and that under great Penalties to believe every thing, or any thing whatever, be it never ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and falſe, for an undoubted Verity, that either the Pope or his Clegy ſhall teach, impoſe or command: And amongſt the reſt, any falſe Miracle: and indeed, they ſhall not need take any great Pains in perſwading their blind People to a Belief; for they are naturally prone to imbibe any Abſurdity, and ſwallow down any Morſel be it never ſo peſtiferous, falſe, vain, deſtructive or tragical: yea, to the murthering of their deareſt and neareſt Relations: by which we may learn, That there is no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging a Papiſt, no, not by the greateſt Kindneſs, and Courteſy imaginable; for, if he will be true to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates and Principles of his own Religion, he muſt ſeek and endeavour the Utter Ruine of Proteſtants, yea, though they ſhould have ſaved him from the Gallows!</p>
            <p>O! Sirs, Who would be of ſo black a Society? of ſo bloody a Religion? who but the worſt of men, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, Idolaters, Tracebreakers, Sots, Ideots or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would ſubject the Faculties of their Souls, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their Bodies, to the imperious VVills and Pleaſure of every proud Prelate and blind Curate? But the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do ſo: <hi>Erge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude my Preface with the Story of a great
<pb facs="tcp:36213:9"/> Popiſh Doctor, Cardinal <hi>Hoſius,</hi> who thereby gives you to underſtand what kind of Believers the BULK of Papiſts are.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Now, I ſhall proceed to my purpoſe, and it matters not if I begin with <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> ſometimes Arch-Flamin of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> Arch-Traytor to his Prince (<hi>Hen. II.</hi>) Arch-Enemy to his Country, and Arch-Friend or grand Vaſſal to his Unholy Holineſs the POPE.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:10"/>
            <head>A PAQUET OF POPISH DELUSIONS, Falſe MIRACLES <hi>and</hi> Lying WONDERS, Publiſhed to the Shame of POPERY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS Man, of whom we are going to ſpeak, was in few years after he was made Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> grown to that height of Pride and Ambition; and to that degree of Inſolence; and into ſuch high Favour with the Pope; that he began not only to ſlight, and domineer over his Fellow-biſhops, but alſo the prime Nobility and Gentry of the whole Kingdom; and not theſe only but the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Henry</hi> II. whom he had often noſed with moſt malepert and ſaucy Language, and proud behaviour: yea, ſo imperious was he grown that he ſuffered (or rather created a kind of neceſſity for it) the King twice in one day to hold his Stirrup in <hi>Normandy:</hi> Until at laſt, he was grown ſo intollerable in his Deport, in ſo much that the King could no longer brook him. Many times would he lament his own ſad Condition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was forc'd to bear with his Pride and Arrogancy, for fear of the Pope. And whilſt he was conſidering what to do with him; Four of his Gentlemen, knowing his mind, and the juſtneſs of the thing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to revenge his quarrel, and do that with their own Swords, which the Pope would not give way to be done by the Sword of Juſtice: And thereupon ſoon after ſlew the Traytor in
<hi>Chriſts Church</hi> in <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No ſooner heard the Pope of the Death of this his great Champion, but he canonized him for a ſhining Saint in Heaven: and ſent the Deed-doers with his black Curſe down to the Pit of Hell, as he thought.</p>
               <p>And, as ſoon as <hi>Stephen Langton,</hi> (his fourth Succeſſor) had made a Golden Shrine for his body, and commanded the annual day of his death to be kept holy: not only the common People, but Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36213:11"/> and Biſhops, not only of this, but other Kingdoms, reſorted in Pilgrimage to his Tomb, in the ſame Church wherein he was done to Death; and flocked to his ſhrine for Remiſſion of Sins: Inſomuch, that multitudes thronged to ſee, touch, yea to kiſs even the vileſt parts of his Body or Relict: Whereby the Church became ſo rich in Offerings of Silver, Gold, Jewels, &amp;c. that it far exceeded the Kings Treaſury: Every Monk and Fryer ſounding forth the Praiſes, and reporting the Miracles, and Pardons of that bleſſed Martyr, as they ſtyled him; (but ſurely it is not the death, but the Cauſe that maker a Martyr) ſo that the name of poor CHRIST was now quite forgotten, and the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral commonly called St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Church of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be too teadious to write of the ſtately Churches, Chappels and Oratories built and dedicated to his Name, and of the blaſphemous Hymns and Collects invented by Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for his honor and Service.</p>
               <p>The Monks of St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> in <hi>Canterbury</hi> perceiving how little their old Reliques were eſteemed in compariſon of
<hi>Thomas Beckets,</hi> they by the Craft of their Abbot, got ſome part of his Blood, and one part of the Crown of his head, the Report whereof brought no ſmall Credit and Profit to their Monaſtery: and tho many thouſands went a whoring e'n to this as well as the other Monaſtery: yet it appear'd in the end, that there was no part of <hi>Becket</hi> brought thither, as it was made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt eſpecially (in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII) by that Worthy Peer <hi>Thomas Cromwell</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and others who were Commiſſioned for defacing <hi>Beckets</hi> ſhrine, and found all parts of his body entire and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, ſo that the blinded People in this one matter were doubly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and deluded: 1. In going to worſhip him or any part of him at all. 2. In worſhipping that which was not there, but only made to believe ſo, by the crafty and ſeducing Monks.</p>
               <p>Now, amongſt the many Miracles that the miſerable deluded Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts will needs have been wrought by this proud Prelate; theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are ſome, if any are ſo mad as to believe them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That his Palace at <hi>Otford</hi> wanting a good Spring of Water, he ſtruck his Paſtoral ſtaff into the ground, and, that immediately Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter guſhed out in abundance (as <hi>Moſes</hi> did) and there runneth to this day; which was called <hi>St. Thomas</hi>'s Well.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That, being at his Devotion in his Park, he was much diſturbed by a <hi>Nightingale</hi> that ſung in a buſh hard by him; and therefore, by the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Holineſs, he enjoyned that from thenceforward no ſuch Bird ſhould preſume to ſing thereabouts: and no more there did, ſay Papiſts, when the contrary is, and was then manifeſt to all the Neighbourhood.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:11"/>3. That the Black-ſmith of the ſaid Town of <hi>Otford</hi> having prick'd his horſe, <hi>Becket</hi> enacted again by the Authority of his Holineſs, That no Smith ſhould thrive in the Pariſh ever after: <hi>Cujus contrarium ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That, <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King coming into
<hi>England</hi> to viſit King <hi>Henry,</hi> and in his Return would needs Viſit St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and, after great Offers at his Tomb, asked and alſo obtained of the holy Saint, That neither he in his Paſſage, nor any other for the future, ſhould ſuffer ſhip-wrack betwixt <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Whitſand:</hi> ſo that it ſeems
<hi>Becket</hi> granted a Petition after his Death. Who can forbear laughing at theſe and ſuch like Tales? However, God ſhew'd his Diſpleaſure againſt him, and all <hi>Canterbury,</hi> perhaps for his ſake, for in the very firſt year of his Prelacy, the whole City was conſumed with fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEſides Saint <hi>Becket,</hi> there was another popiſh Saintling in great Veneration at <hi>Otford</hi> (in Saxon <hi>Ottanford</hi>) his name was <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew,</hi> this Higler provided the Pariſh-prieſt with as much Poultry as he and his Friends were able to devour; for he was much frequented by all the Neighbour Pariſhioners, for a moſt rare and ſingular property which he profeſſed.</p>
               <p>For the Manner was, That, if any woman with Child deſired to bring forth a Son, ſhe ſhould offer to this St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> a Cock-chicken: &amp; if ſhe would have a Daughter, then ſhe ſhould preſent him an Hen: ſo that through the fraud of this Fox, <hi>viz.</hi> Prieſt, the Country People, as wiſe as Capons, were many years together robbed of their Cocks and Hens: even till the daies of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. who underſtanding the Cheat, commanded the Idol to be taken down.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEda</hi> (whoſe writing are ſtuffed with old Wives tales) informs us, that upon a time, a great part of the City of
<hi>Canterbury</hi> being on fire, That the then Arch-biſhop, <hi>viz. Melitus</hi> commanded, that they ſhould bear him againſt the greateſt fury thereof; and that whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could not be quenched by the great labour of the People, yet at his only preſence, together with Holy-water, the fire immediately went out, 'Tis wonder why <hi>Becket</hi> did not the ſame in his time, but perhaps he was in a journey, as <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid of
<hi>Balaam,</hi> No Proteſtant hath <pb facs="tcp:36213:12"/> reaſon to believe this, nor any ſuch Tales, at which ſo many learned Papiſts laugh in their ſleeves. The mentioning of Holy-water brings to my Memory this Paſſage concerning it:</p>
               <p>A Proteſtant Boy (very well known to me) put a pretty Trick upon a Prieſt, and all his blind Congregation: Thus, in the Morning, a little before Maſs-time, the Boy obſerving where the Prieſt had ſet his pot of Holy-water, takes the pot, pours out all the Holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and piſſes in it, ſo ſets it in its place again: ſoon after the Prieſt takes the pot, and all beſprinkles the people with the Piſs, and they very reverently b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w down to it, and perceiving that the Water would not hold out to bleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em all, they thruſt forward ſtriving who ſhould come neareſt the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, for fear they ſhould go away unbleſſ'd. But the Prieſt knowing he had fill'd the pot, was greatly amazed to ſee it all gone ſo ſoon; and thereupon, ſmelling to the Bottle, croſſed (not bleſſed) himſelf: and, to ſatisfie his blind People (who were as much amaz'd as himſelf) he told them, <hi>That, no doubt but ſome Saint or Angel had got away the reſt!</hi> And they without any heſitation believed him.
<figure/> 
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36213:12"/> But in a year or two, the Buſineſs came all out, and they with their Prieſt were well laughed at by the Proteſtants. However they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Boy with Deſtruction, as the Prieſt did with Damnation; ſo that for this and other matters, done and ſaid againſt Popery, he was forced to fly his Country, and live
<hi>incognito,</hi> as he does to this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>IV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny Miracles are ſaid to be wrought by Saint
<hi>Augustine</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and by many ſtiled the Engliſh <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> and no doubt were as true as the reſt: I ſhall not blot Paper with any of them, ſave this one,
<hi>viz.</hi> When the <hi>Danes</hi> had plundered the City from end to end, (<hi>as the Papiſts long to ſerve London</hi>). Yet Saint
<hi>Auguſtines</hi> Monks and Monaſtery were never touch'd! and why? Becauſe that when a Dane had taken hold of his Cloak where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his Tomb was covered; it ſtuck ſo faſt to his Fingers, that by no means poſſible he could looſen it, till he came and yielded himſelf to the Monks and confeſſed his fault.</p>
               <p>But, either this Cloak (ſaith my Author) was weaved <hi>ex auro Tholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſano,</hi> or, which I rather believe) this Canterbury-tale was forged <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula Romano.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>V.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOT far from <hi>Hyde</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> there was a Popiſh Synagogue, ſtil'd St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Chappel: to this Saint, the Fryers attributed Power over the Winds and Waves of the Sea; yea, that with his own Beck he could appeaſe them, and preſerve from Wrack and Drowning, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as called upon his Name (but they muſt withall offer largely to his Picture.) And this was confidently believed by the Idolatrous people, as well ſeamen as others. If any Fiſherman upon that coaſt had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a ſtorm, then ſhould St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> have not only all the thanks for that Deliverance, but ſome of the beſt fiſhes for an offering. But if any ſuffer'd Wreck (as many did) the Prieſt to ſave the Repute of the Saint, would ſay, <hi>It was becauſe they offered too niggardly, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was the like Cheat at <hi>Wind-Chelſey,</hi> in which place was the Picture of St. <hi>Leonard</hi> holding a Vane, or Weathercock in his hand, which was movable at the pleaſure of any that would turn it to what point of the Compaſs beſt fitted the Return of the Husband or other Friend whom they expected from beyond Sea. After that done, and <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36213:13"/> large offering made (for without offering theſe Idols would be idle) they promiſed themſelves the deſired Wind, but whether it fell out right or wrong the Prieſts got well by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>VI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis that I am now upon, as it is one of the longeſt Stories, ſo, in my Judgment, it is one of the moſt notorious E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of all the reſt, or at leaſt equal to the blackeſt of them: f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, it was deviſed and carryed on with ſuch wonderful craft and Secreſy, That not only the Vulgar, but the whole Gentry and Nobility of both Sexes, and many men of the greateſt Learning and Judgment were for a time bewitched, and ſtrangely and ſtrongly poſſeſt with falſe apprehenſions of the Truth thereof; and many of them Proteſtants too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In relation whereof I ſhall for the moſt part, deliver it in my Authors own words.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>About <hi>Eaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> in the 7 year of <hi>Hen. 8. An<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
1525<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it happened that a certain Maid named <hi>Elizabeth Barton</hi> (by the Papiſts called the <hi>Holy Maid of</hi> Kent) was afflicted with a ſtrange Diſeaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the Convulſion fits (for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ſhe ſeemed to be dead) and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had thus continued by fits, ſome
7 months, in one of her fits: ſhe asked if the child was dead? (for her Maſters child lay deſperately ſick in the Cradle) 'twas anſwered, No: It ſhall dy anon, ſaid ſhe, and ſo it did, for every body ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it, whether ſhe had ſaid it or not.</p>
               <p>But this ſaving of hers concerning the Childs death, was by ſeveral (ignorant of the childs dying Condition at the ſame inſtant) blazed about for a wonder, and ſhe termed no leſs than a Propheteſs.</p>
               <p>After this, in ſundry other Fits (though ſhe ſeemed to be dead) ſhe told of divers things done at the Church, and other places where ſhe was not preſent. She ſpake of Heaven, Hell and Purgatory; and of the Joyes, and Sorrows that ſeveral Souls departed ſuffered there. She prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much againſt the Corruption of Manners, and evil Living. She ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to hearing the Maſs, Auricular Confeſſion, Adoration and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Saints and our Lady. In ſhort, ſhe made, in all points, Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Popiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36213:13"/>And among other things, this was much in her mouth, viz. <hi>She would go home;</hi> and yet ſhe never ſtirred from the Place ſhe lay. Whereupon (being in her Fits) one ask'd her, Where that Home was? She anſwered, <hi>Where ſhe heard and ſaw the Joyes of Heaven; where St.</hi> Michael <hi>weighed Souls; where St.</hi> Peter <hi>carried the Keyes, and where ſhe herſelf had the Company of our Lady of</hi> Courtop-ſtreet;
<hi>and, had heartily beſought her to heal her diſeaſe: who alſo had commanded her, to offer her a Taper in her Chappel there: And to declare boldly to all Chriſtian People, That our La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of</hi> Courtop-ſtreet (a Town near the Borders of
<hi>Rumny-marſh) had revived her from the very point of death, and, that her pleaſure was, That it ſhould be rung for a Miracle.</hi> which her Maſter (Mr. <hi>Cob</hi> of <hi>Aldington</hi>) hearing, ſaid, That there were no Bells in that Chappel: whereto ſhe ſaid nothing. But the voice (or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil) that ſpake in her proceeded, ſaying, <hi>Our Lady will ſhew more Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles there ſhortly; for, if any depart this life ſuddenly, or in deadly Sin, if he be vowed to our Lady heartily, he ſhall be reſtored to life again to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſhr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and houſel,</hi> i. e. be confeſt, and have the Sacrament given: <hi>and after to leav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this World with Gods bleſſing.</hi> Beſides this, <hi>She told them what meat the Monk, or Hermet of our Ladies Chappel of</hi> Courtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet <hi>had for his ſupper;</hi> whereat (ſaith her popiſh Scribe) the hearers marvelled greatly.</p>
               <p>And, from that time forward, ſhe reſolv'd with herſelf to go to <hi>Courtop ſtreet</hi> (not far off) and there pray, and offer to our Lady, which ſhe did accordingly; and was there delayed of her Cure for a ſeaſon (and that was till her dying day, for ſhe was never cured) but yet in the mean time put in aſſured hope thereof.</p>
               <p>During theſe Matters, the Fame of this marvelous Maiden ſpread abroad ſo, that it came to the ears of <hi>Wareham</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury:</hi> who ſent to her Dr. <hi>Bocking, Barnes</hi> and <hi>Hadley,</hi> three Monks, Father <hi>Lewes</hi> and his Fellow: his Official, and the Parſon of <hi>Alding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton:</hi> with Commiſſion to examine the whole matter.</p>
               <p>Theſe men, finding her every way a true Child of the Church of
<hi>Rome:</hi> not only waded no further in detecting of ſo great a Fraud; but gave favorable Countenance, and joyned with her in ſetting forth the ſame. So, that at her next Journey to our Lady of <hi>Courtop-ſtreet,</hi> ſhe entred the Chappel with <hi>Ave Regina Caelorum,</hi> in prick ſong, accompanied with theſe Commiſſioners, many Ladys, Gentlemen, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen of the beſt degree, with three thouſand of the Vulgar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. Being in the Chappel, ſhe immediately fell into a wonderful Paſſion before the Image, as if ſhe had the Falling Sickneſs (like <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet.</hi>)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36213:14"/> in which ſhe uttered ſundry m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trical and rhyming Speeches, tending to the Worſhip of the Lady of <hi>Courtop-ſtreet</hi> (as ſhe called her:) whoſe Chappel there ſhe wiſhed to be better maintained, and to be furniſhed with a daily ſinging prieſt: neither did ſhe forget herſelf, for ſhe ſaid, It was our Ladies pleaſure, That ſhe ſhould be put into ſome Nunnery. Whereupon the Arch Biſhop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ordered her to that of S. <hi>Sepulchers</hi> in <hi>Canterbury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> where ſhe was ſtill afflicted with her former Diſeaſe for all her promiſed Cure.</p>
               <p>Whiles ſhe reſided here, and continued her accuſtomed working of Miracles, (but what they were, none can tell) having often commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with our Lady of <hi>Courtopſtreet,</hi> (as ſhee ſaid) who alſo cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to ſhew herſelf mighty in operation there, for ſhe lighted Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles without fire, reſtore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſick to perfect health, and raiſed the dead to life, if you will believe it.</p>
               <p>Thus was <hi>Elizabeth Barton</hi> advanced, from the Condition of a poor ſervant, to the State of a glorious Nunn, the Hermit or Monk of
<hi>Courtopſtreet</hi> enriched by daily offering; Saint <hi>Sepulchres</hi> honored with the preſence of <hi>the Holy Maid of Kent,</hi> God blaſphemed, and the bleſſed Virgin abuſed, the ſilly People miſerably mock'd: the Biſhops, Prieſts and Monks in the mean time with cloſed eyes winking, and the Devil with open mouth laughing at it. And thus the matter ſtood for ſundry years: till the Queſtion was moved about the Kings Divorce:</p>
               <p>Whereupon this holy Wench (not contenting her ſelf within her former bounds of Hypocriſy) began to meddle in that Matter: and feigned, That it was revealed to her, That if the King would be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from Queen
<hi>Katherine,</hi> he ſhould not be King one month after, (though after the Divorce he lived proſperouſly many years.)</p>
               <p>Upon which, her doings were once again examined by faithful men; and in the end, her diſſimulation was laid open; her Acceſſaries the Monks <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were detected, the deluded people well ſatisfied; the grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers Worthily executed: and the Pope and the Devil, their Maſter quite and clean confounded. For <hi>E. Barton,</hi> her ſelf confeſſed the whole Cheat to the Lords of the Privy Counci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: Whereof you may ſee more in the 12 Chapter of the Statute in the 25 year of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. And moſt of them, which have been Sainted by Popes, for theſe 1000 years (I believe) are little better than this She-Impoſtor. O what a ſhame is this one Story to Popery, if Papiſts had any ſhame in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="delusion">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36213:14"/>
               <head>Deluſion <hi>VII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF Saint <hi>Eanſwid</hi> (ſo called) daughter of
<hi>Eadbald</hi> King of <hi>Kent,</hi> many lying Wonders are reported,
<hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe lengthned the great Beam of a building three Foot, when the Carpenters (miſtaking their Meaſure) had made it ſo much too ſhort. That in the Might of her holineſs ſhe brought Water, over hills and rocks againſt Nature, to her Pryory a mile off. That ſhe forbad certain ravenous Birds the Country, which before did much harm. That ſhe reſtored the blind; Caſt out Devils; and healed all Infirmities. I believe this to be as true, as that <hi>Ed. Gennings</hi> his Thumb came off with the touch of a Pope-holy Siſter.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>Eanſwide,</hi> for theſe her ſtupendious Miracles was after her death, by the Policy of Popiſh Prieſts, and folly of Common People, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored for a Saint. And 'tis no Wonder, for it was, and is ſtill, uſual with the whole Rabble of Romiſh Clergy, not only to magnify their Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of all ſorts, but even to Deify them, eſpecially ſuch as were of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Extraction: Knowing hereby many great Benefits accrewed: as,
1. By that means they aſſured to themſelves many great Perſonages, as Kings and Princes. 2. They drew by their Example infinite numbers of the common ſort after them. 3. They adventure the more Boldly (under thoſe honorable and glorious Names and Titles) to publiſh their falſe Miracle, the more ſtrongly to delude. And this was the Reaſon that <hi>Sexburg</hi> in
<hi>Shepy. Mildred</hi> in <hi>Thanet. Etheldred</hi> at <hi>Ely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Edith</hi> at <hi>Wilton,</hi> and this our <hi>Eanſwid</hi> at
<hi>Folkston:</hi> and ſundry other idle Goſſips of Royal blood, in this and other Nations were ſainted by the Pope. Hence was it alſo, that
<hi>Edgar, Ethelwold, Dunſtane</hi> the Juggler, and many others were ſhrined here on Earth, and then to ſit among the Saints in Heaven. If this
<hi>Eanſwide</hi> had ſuch Power from above, then why did ſhe not preſerve her Pryory from the Fury of <hi>H.</hi> 8. in whoſe daies all her pretended Miracles were openly derided.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SWithin</hi> was Sainted by the Man of <hi>Rome,</hi> for making a Basket of broken Eggs whole, if you will believe the blind Papiſts, who ſwear it with as much Confidence as if they had ſeen it done: tho 'tis many hundred of years ſince <hi>Swithin</hi> was in <hi>orbe noſtro.</hi> And all theſe <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends</hi> were diviſed to bring Credit and Profit to the Romiſh Church: whereat even little Children laugh in Scorn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And in good Truth, moſt <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36213:15"/> Papiſts have as much reaſon to curſe their own Plot and Plotters as we have; and wiſh it had never been: for hereby they have ſet ſo many Proteſtant Pens on Work to lay open the falſneſs, bloodineſs, execrable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ridiculouſneſs and abſurdneſs of their popiſh Religion to the world: which otherwiſe had been ſnent. For, before, People had a pretty good Opinion of the Papiſts; and would ſpeak favorably of them: yea, and many of their Religion too: but now, they both hate them, and their Religion, for the means aforeſaid: ſo that the more they ſtir, the more they ſtink in Peoples noſtrils. I ſay again, That their helliſh PLOT, which intended the utter Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Cauſe, ſeems to me rather an Advantage to it. Yea, though thouſands of Proteſtants ſhould fall by the hands of Papiſts: which yet would but confirm and illuſtrate that divine and glorious Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm, or Motto of the true Church, <hi>viz. Sanguis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> i. e.
<hi>The Blood of the Martyrs is the Seed of the Church.</hi> And I muſt affirm, That <hi>in ſanguine Sanctorum Eccleſiae Papiſticorum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiam obtinuit,</hi> i. e. <hi>The Popiſh Church obtained the Primacy by ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the blood of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>IX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>STrange things ae told us of St. <hi>Mildred</hi> (Lady Abbeſs of <hi>Minſter</hi>-Abby in the Iſle of <hi>Thanet</hi>) no matter whether they be true or no; but the Papiſts will ſwear it. This Saint (ſay they) was ſo mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſended with divine Power, that lying in an hot Oven three hours together, ſuffered no harm. That ſhe was of ſuch virtue, That coming out of <hi>France,</hi> the very ſtone, on which ſhe firſt ſtept to land, receiv'd the Impreſſion of her foot, and retaind it for ever; having beſides this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, that if it were removed never ſo far from its place, it would in ſhort time return of it ſelf without hand. Alſo, that ſhe being at her devotions, the Devil put out her Candle, which an Angel lighted for her again. Who but Reprobates cannot ſee, that the Deluſions and Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Myſtical Babylon (<hi>Rome</hi>) far exceed thoſe of literal Babylon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>X.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I know not whether this I am now upon may be called a Miracle or no, but I am ſure it is one of the lowdeſt Lies that ever came out of the mouth of a Biſhop; and in good Truth I can ſcarce write for laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at it. For, <hi>Henry</hi> Bp. of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> in the Reign of
<hi>Henry</hi> III. K. <pb facs="tcp:36213:15"/> of <hi>England,</hi> mounting the Pulpit at <hi>Sittingbourn,</hi> and as he was in the midſt of his Preachment, he on a ſuddain broke forth into a great Exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy of Joy, as one that had bin wrapt into the third Heaven; and ſaid, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord, my Brethren all; and, Knowye aſſuredly, That now of late in one day, there departed out of Purgatory,</hi> Richard, <hi>ſometime King of</hi> England, Stephen Langton <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain of his, to go to the Divine Majesty; and on that day there iſſued no more but them three out of that place of Pain. Fear not to give full and aſſured Credit to theſe my Words: for this thing hath been now the third time revealed to me, and another man</hi> (in terra incognita) <hi>and that ſo plainly, as from my own mind, all ſuspicion of doubt is far removed.</hi> No doubt but this was as true, as that the Cow eat <hi>Tom Thumb,</hi> and ſent him alive once more into the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You may ſee with what wholeſom Cates Prelates uſed to feed the People: And if the Biſhops, the great Torches gave ſuch a dim Light, what could be expected from ruſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, their blind Curates, and other filly ſir-<hi>Johns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning Purgatory, <hi>Virgil</hi> will ſhew you what agreement there is between the Old <hi>Romans</hi> and the New
<hi>Romaniſts,</hi> in theſe Verſes, 1. 6. <hi>Aenead.</hi>
               </p>
               <l>Quin &amp; ſupremo cum lumine vita relinquit,</l>
               <l>Non tamen omne malum miſeris, nec funditus omnes,</l>
               <l>Corporeae excedunt peſtes, penitusque neceſſe eſt</l>
               <l>Multa diu concreta, modis inoleſcere miris.</l>
               <l>Ergo exercentur poenis, veterum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> malorum</l>
               <l>Supplicia expendunt. Aliae panduntur inanes</l>
               <l>Suſpenſae ad ventos, aliis ſub gurgite vaſto</l>
               <l>Infectum eluitur ſcelus, aut exuritur igni:</l>
               <l>Quiſque ſuos patimur Manes: exinde per amplum</l>
               <l>Mittimur Elyſium, &amp; pauci laeta arva tenemus:</l>
               <l>Donec longa dies, perſecto temporis orbe,</l>
               <l>Concretam exemit labem, purumque reliquit</l>
               <l>Aetherium ſenſum, atque aurai ſimplicis ignem.</l>
               <lg>
                  <head>Thus Paraphras'd.</head>
                  <l>Moreover, when their end of Life, and light do them forſake,</l>
                  <l>Yet can they not their ſins nor ſorrows all (poor Souls!) off ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Nor all Contagions fleſhly from them voids, but muſt of need,</l>
                  <l>Much things congendred long, by wondrous means at last out-ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Therefore they plagued are, and for their former faults and ſins,</l>
                  <l>Their ſundry pains they bide: ſome high in air do hang on pins:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36213:16"/>Some fleeting are in Flouds, and deep in gulfs themſelves they tire,</l>
                  <l>'Till ſins away are waſh'd, or cleaenſed clean with purging fire,</l>
                  <l>Each one of us our Penance here abide, that ſent we be</l>
                  <l>To Paradiſe at last: we few theſe fields of joy do ſee.</l>
                  <l>Till compaſs long of time, by perfect courſe hath purged quite,</l>
                  <l>Our former clodedred ſpots, and pure hath left our ghostly ſprite,</l>
                  <l>And ſenſes pure of Soul, and ſimple ſparks of heavenly light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Now, if this Biſhops Poetry may be allowed for Divinity, then we may not only affirm, That <hi>Virgil's</hi> Aeniedes, but <hi>Homer's</hi> Iliads, <hi>Ovid's</hi> Faſts, and <hi>Lucians</hi> Dialogues alſo may be made Canonical.</p>
               <p>All the Scriptures that the Papiſts bring to prove a Purgatory (which yet is no Canonical Scripture) is out of <hi>Maccabes</hi> 2. 12. You ſee how hard they are put to it, that they muſt fly to the Apocrypha for help; though all the World of knowing Chriſtians in all Ages, to this day, have utterly rejected the Authority thereof, in compariſon of the Old and New Teſtament, becauſe not penned by the Holy Ghoſt. And wherein (as I could prove) are not only flat Contradictions, but ſome Lies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Image of <hi>Edith,</hi> the Daughter of King
<hi>Edgar,</hi> was much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented in the Church yard at <hi>Kemſing,</hi> for preſervation of Corn from Blaſſing, Mildew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner of which Idolatry was this. The blind Farmer or Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was to bring about a Buſhel of Corn to the Church, and after Prayers made, offered it to the Image of the Saint. Of this offering the Prieſt uſed to take nine Parts for himſelf (for to be ſure he would gain by the Bargain) the reſidue (perhaps 2 or 3 handful) he would beſprinkle with holy Water, and then mutter over a few Words of Conjuration, which done he dedicated it to the Image, and ſo delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to the Fool that brought it; who went away with full perſwaſion That if he mingled that hallowed handful with all his Seed-corn, it would preſerve it not only from harm, but cauſed it to proſper and grow moſt abundantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Terentius Varro</hi> noteth of the Old <hi>Romans,</hi> that amongſt infinite others, they had one God in great Veneration, called
<hi>Robigus,</hi> to whom they uſed to ſacrifice for preſervation of their Corn; ſo that <hi>Robigus</hi> of the Old <hi>Romans,</hi> and
<hi>Edith</hi> of the New <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> were both wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped for the ſame end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And they not only agreed in this, but in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36213:16"/> Properties of their Gods, in the manner and multitude of their Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the times and forms of their Solemnities, in the Report of their al ſe and ſeigned Miracles: and almoſt in the whole Heap and Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of their filthy Superſtitions and Idolatries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plautus,</hi> though an heathen Poet indeed, yet in this more heavenly than any Papiſt, gives all men this following Counſel, thereby intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that they ſhould worſhip but one God, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus dum tibi propitius est Jupiter, tu hoſce minutos deos flocci feceris, i. e.</hi> Whilſt Jupiter is thy friend, ſet not a ſtraw by all the Petty Gods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12,13" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XII. XIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EAdred,</hi> a blind Abbot, did wonderfully magnify him they cal-St. <hi>Edward,</hi> or <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, becauſe he ſo much magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Monkiſh manner of living. Therefore the ſaid Abbot moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently affirmeth, <hi>That the ſame King, while he heard Maſs at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, <hi>ſaw between the Prieſts hands, Christ bleſſing him with his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> That at another Maſs, <hi>He ſaw the 7 Sleepers at</hi> Epheſus <hi>turn themſelves, after they had ſlept
70 years on the other.</hi> Alſo, <hi>That St.</hi> John Baptiſt ſent the ſame <hi>St.</hi> Edward (can any King be a Saint!) <hi>a gold Ring from Jeruſalem, which he himſelf had ſometime given to a poor man that asked alms of him in the name of S.</hi> John.</p>
               <p>I believe S. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> is as much belyed and abuſed in this kind, as any Saint whatever, and by none more than by the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for in the County of <hi>Eaſt Meath</hi> at (or very near) <hi>Dunſaney,</hi> there is a Well dedicated to his Name, of which many hyperbolical Tales are report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all the Cures done there (as they ſay, there have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) are wholy attributed to St. <hi>John</hi> by the blind people, thereby giving to the Creature, the glory due to the Creator. Poſſibly ſome may have ſound good in going to that Well, in ſome ailments (as they may at other Wells both in <hi>Ireland, England,</hi> &amp;c.) but it is by the only Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God who hath put Virtue in that, and other waters; and not in the leaſt by any operation or Mediation of St.
<hi>John,</hi> or any other Saint, as the Papiſts dream.</p>
               <p>Here take another ſtrange Tale reported of a Gentleman that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time lived hard by the ſame Well. His name was <hi>Waren</hi> or
<hi>Waring,</hi> commonly ſtiled <hi>Waring</hi> of the Well. This perſon would needs v. ſit the holy Lard (ſo called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) And when he arrived there, or thereabouts, one day paſſing a River, his pilgrims ſtaff by chance ſlipt out of his hand into the River, and by the violence of the Stream was carried quite <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36213:17"/> away, to the great grief of our Pilgrim, becauſe the ſtaff had been hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and had a Crucifix and other knacks upon it. But behold! what ſtrange luck this man had: For, at his return home, or, before it, (for I have almoſt forgot the ſtory) his ſtaff was found at the Well afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, about 3000 miles diſtance from the River where it gave him the Slip. I have heard this hotly affirmed by ſeveral Prieſts and Fryers for a moſt certain Truth: and the return of the Staff they aſcribe to St. <hi>John B.</hi> If this and the reſt be not lyes, then the Devil never told any: But indeed, I have known this, and many other pretended Mirac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es laughed at by ſeveral lay-Papiſts, as mere Fictions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIlliam</hi> the Monk of <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> writing of
<hi>Alpheus</hi> or <hi>Alphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſometime Biſhop of
<hi>Canterbury</hi> (whom he and his fellow-Monks will needs have ſtiled a Saint) affirmeth, <hi>That a dead ſtick being (after his Death) anointed with his blood, ſuddenly waxed green again: and</hi> (like <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, Num. 17. 8.) <hi>began to bloſſom the next day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No doubt, but this is as true, as that the heathen Goddeſs,
<hi>Dea fero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> (as pope like Poets fable) <hi>cauſed an whole Wood that was on fire, to wax green again:</hi> Of whom <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith,
<hi>Et viridi gaudens feronia luco.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XIV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AShurſt,</hi> in that point of <hi>Kent</hi> bordering upon <hi>Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Sarry,</hi> though now a poor ſmale Village, yet in old time moſt famous for the ſake of a <hi>Rood,</hi> which had ſuch a rare property, that multitudes of people came hundreds of mile to adore it.</p>
               <p>For the Popiſh Clergy blazed about (and the common people believ'd any thing they ſaid, tho never ſo ridiculous or abſurd.)
<hi>That the Rood, or</hi> Crucifix) <hi>of this Church, did by certain Increments continually wax and grow, as well in the buſh of hair (or Periwig) that it had on its head as alſo in the length and ſtature of the Members, and body it ſelf.</hi> By which Invention it came to paſs, that the Pariſh-prieſt (before ſcarce able to ſubſiſt, his Incoms were ſo ſmall) did not only live moſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly, but alſo hoordid up much money: Whilſt, he and his reverend Brethren, laughed in their Sleeves, at the blinded people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15,16" type="delusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:36213:17"/>
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XV. XVI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF <hi>Juſtus,</hi> a <hi>quandam</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Rochester,</hi> the Monks report this for a great Miracle: <hi>That when his Body, many years after Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, was to be removed to</hi> Canterbury,
<hi>it yielded a moſt ſweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſmell to all that were preſent:</hi> which thing, how ſtrange it was, when he had been before his Interment embalmed with moſt precious and odoriferous Spices; Let any man judge, that hath not reſolv'd to believe all manner of Deluſions.</p>
               <p>But I have not done with <hi>Rochester,</hi> having another Saint and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles to tell you of. The Monaſtery of this City being erected by <hi>Gundulphus</hi> their Biſhop, having with its Monks ſuffer'd many Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, 1. as being twice burned in leſs Compaſs than one hundred years. 2. Through the great Contentions ariſing betwixt them and their Bp.
<hi>Gilbert Glanvile</hi> (who alwayes hated Monks) in ſo much that he in great diſpleaſure bereaved them, not only of their goods, Ornaments and Writings, but alſo of a great part of their Lands, Poſſeſſions and Priviledges: and they (turmoil'd themſelves in ſuit to the Pope, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and for their Charges) were driven to coin their Silver ſhrine of
<hi>Paulinus</hi> into ready Money; which Act of theirs wholy took away the Eſtimation of their Church, and that reverence which the blind People before ſhewed their Saint <hi>Paulinus:</hi> To theſe Calamities were added other great Loſſes ſuſtained through the Wars of King <hi>John,</hi> who in his Siege againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Rochester,</hi> ſo ſpoil'd this Church and Priory that he left them not ſo much as one poor <hi>Pix</hi> to ſtand upon their Altar.</p>
               <p>Therefore, it was now high time to deviſe ſome way whereby the Priory might be, if not altogether reſtored to its former ſplendor, yet at leaſt, ſomewhat relieved from this preſent penury and abjection.</p>
               <p>To bring this about, the crafty Monks, had by degrees drawn the ſilly people to think very reverendly of one <hi>William,</hi> that lay buried in the Church: and knowing by Experience, that there was no one way in the world ſo conducible to their profit, as the advancement of a Pilgrimage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore they procured of the Pope, the canonization of the ſaid <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam:</hi> with Indulgence to all ſuch as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld offer at his Tomb.</p>
               <p>But to the end that it may appear to what hard ſhift for a Saint theſe popelings were driven, and how eaſie the wretched people were then deluded, you ſhall hear what great man this Saint <hi>William</hi> of
<hi>Rochester</hi> was.</p>
               <p>Indeed, he was a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> born at
<hi>Saint-Johnstown,</hi> a Baker by Trade, in (blind) zeal ſo fervent, That he vowed to viſit the Holy land <pb facs="tcp:36213:18"/> (as they call it) and in his way paſſed thro <hi>Rochester,</hi> where having a while refreſh'd himſelf, he marched towards <hi>Canterbury;</hi> but he had not gon far from
<hi>Rochester,</hi> but either his ſervant (or ſome high way men) robb'd him both of his Life and Money: and becauſe he dyed in ſo holy a purpoſe of mind (forſooth) the Monks conveyed him to St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> laid him in the quire; and was promoted by the Pope (as you heard) from a poor Baker, to a bleſſed Martyr: and wrought Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles as faſt as <hi>Bell</hi> (in the
<hi>Apocrypha</hi>) eat Mutton. However, it is certain, that mad Folks offered liberally to him, even till the daies of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17,18" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XVII, XVIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEEing <hi>Stroud</hi> is ſo near, let's paſs over the Bridg, and hear what was done there to St. <hi>Thomas Beckets</hi> horſe, and how he was revenged on the Deed-doers. The Story is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St. Thomas</hi> (ſaith <hi>Polidore <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil,</hi> the Popes Sycophant, and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his <hi>Peter</hi>-pence in <hi>England</hi>) being hated of the King, (<hi>Hen.</hi> 2.) and commonly neglected and deſpiſed; that when, one time, he hapn'd to paſs through <hi>Stroud,</hi> either ſome of the Inhabitants, or one <hi>Robert Brock</hi> of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> cut off the tail of <hi>Beckots</hi> horſe, for which act it ſo hapen'd (by the will of God, ſaith <hi>Polidore</hi>) that all the poſterity of them that had plai'd that naughty prank, were born with tails, even as bruit beaſts are. And this is the very Reaſon, that as
<hi>Kentiſh</hi> men are in meriment called <hi>Kentiſh long-tails,</hi> at home; ſo all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> in foreign parts are flouted, eſpecially by the Vulgar, who have bin made believe by their Clergy, that the Engliſh were Monſters, and have tails by nature. Hence it is, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> call them STARTS. But no people d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d believe it ſo much as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> (thoſe ancient and moſt inverterate Enemies of <hi>England</hi>) tho at laſt they became of another mind: for King <hi>James</hi> having ſent an Embaſſador into
<hi>Spain,</hi> with an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of many brave Gentlemen, the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> very earneſtly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and viewed them whether they had tails or no, but finding they had none, and the Report to be falſe, they railed at their Clergy, who had told it for a certain truth.</p>
               <p>Such another like Story is reported of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the <hi>Engliſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,</hi> and <hi>Beckets</hi> Predeceſſor; who (as the ſame Author ſaith) when fiſh-tails were deſpitefully thrown at him by ſome in <hi>Dorſet-ſhire</hi> (at <hi>Miglington</hi> ſaies
<hi>Hector Boetius</hi>) the meek Prelate grew thereat into ſuch a Fary, that
<hi>He called upon God for Revenge, who forthwith heard him, and ſtruck them with Tails for their Puniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36213:18"/>He that believes this or any of the reſt, I am ſure did never rightly believed in God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before I proceed any further in theſe lying Wonders, Let me, for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion ſake, and to make my Reader a little ſport, give you an account of a Religious Skirmiſh, between the Monks of</hi> Rocheſter,
<hi>and the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of</hi> Stroud <hi>Hoſpital.</hi> The ſaid Monks, by reaſon of a great Drought, agreed among themſelves to make a ſolemn Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their own houſe thorow the City, and ſo to
<hi>Friendsbury,</hi> on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Water, of a ſpecial intent and purpoſe to pray to God for Rain: and becauſe the day of this their appointed Journy hapned to be very boyſterous and windy, the which would not only have blown out their Lights, and toſſed their Banners, but have ſtop'd the mouths of their ſinging men, and toiled them in their heavy and masking attire; they deſir'd licenſe of the Maſter of
<hi>Stroud</hi>-hoſpital, to paſs thorow the Orchard of his Houſe, whereby they might both eaſe themſelves, and ſave the glory of their Shew.</p>
               <p>The Maſter eaſily aſſented to their Requeſt, but acquainted not his brethren with it: who, ſo ſoon as they heard of it, called to mind that their Hoſpital was founded by <hi>Gilbert Glanvile,</hi> ſomtime Biſhop of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> between whom and the Predeceſſors of theſe Monks there had been great heats for the Erection of the ſame. Therefore, fearing that the Monks, pretending a Proceſſion, intended to attempt ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Priviledges, they reſolv'd with all might and main to reſiſt them. And for that purpoſe (unknown to their Maſter) they furniſht themſelves, and others that aſſiſted them, with Bats, Clubs and Coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaves, and ſo laid in Ambuſh for the Monks coming into their Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, who little dream'd what was preparing for them.</p>
               <p>It was not long, but the Monks (having made all things ready) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd in their Battel aray, with their Banners diſplay'd, and ſo (think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no harm at all) entred the hoſpital boldly, through which they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the Orchard, merrily chanting their Latin Letany: but when the Brethren and their Auxiliaries eſpied them within their danger, they ruſh'd out of their lurking holes, ran upon them, and made it rain ſuch a ſhour of Bats and Clubs upon the Monks Copes, Cowls, and Crowns, that for a while the miſerable men knew not which way to turn them.</p>
               <p>After they had a little recollected their wits (of which, through meer amazement they had been a while bereaved) and making Vertue of the Neceſſity, and the beſt ſhift they could for themſelves: Some tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſing their ground, declined many blows, yet now and then bore off <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36213:19"/> with head and ſhoulders; others uſed the ſtaves of their Croſſes, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves like pretty men: ſome made pikes of their Banner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles; others cloſing with their adverſaries, wreſted their weapons out of their hands: among the reſt, one (ſaving his Charity) laid load on a married Prieſt, abſolving him <hi>à Culpa,</hi> but not <hi>à Poena:</hi> another drave one of the brethren into a ditch: a third, as big as any <hi>Bull of Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an,</hi> ran at the back door of the Orchard ſo vehemently with his head and ſhoulders, that he bore it clear down before him, and ſo both eſcaped himſelf, and made way for his fellows, who with all poſſible ſpeed conveyed themſelves out of the Precincts of the Hoſpital: and then, ſhaking their ears, they fell afreſh to their <hi>Orgia,</hi> I would ſay, to their <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this Storm was blown (or rather born) over, I do not wonder if the Monks never ſought to carry their Proceſſion through
<hi>Stroud</hi>-Hoſpital, to avoid the wind; for indeed it could not likely blow more boiſterous out of any quarter. And thus, out of this tragical hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, aroſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by-word of <hi>Frindsbury Bats.</hi> And altho there was none ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain in this holy War, yet I make no doubt but that they were ſo well dreſſed, that they had cauſe to remember it many years after.</p>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wever, the Brethren of the hoſpital, for <hi>Penance</hi> of their fault, were injoyned every <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Munday to come into <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chester</hi> in way of Proceſſion with their Crabs: for this their offence (it ſeems) was never to be forgiven, whilſt the Monks remained. I doubt ſome of theſe Monks had forgot to carry their <hi>Agnus Dei's</hi> about them, which, as the blind Papiſts believe, will defend a man from all Enemies, even from the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf: but this <hi>Legend</hi> is like the reſt, and can be diſproved in many Papiſts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. and more lately in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> where thouſands were found dead with their
<hi>Agnus Dei</hi>'s about them. And a certain great Papiſt being to paſs near the Enemies Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, his Confeſſor ask'd him, if he had his
<hi>Agnus Dei</hi> with him? he anſwer'd, No. <hi>O, by any means</hi> (ſaid the Prieſt) <hi>Take it with you, or you will come to ſome harm:</hi> ſo he took it, but before he had gone ſix miles he was kill'd and ſtript of all. Here you ſee what Virtue was in the <hi>Agnus Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I was a Boy, I had a longing deſire to know what an
<hi>Agnus D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> was, becauſe Papiſts youths my School fellows kept ſuch ſtir about them, as if no Angel could guard a man better (as they ſaid, their Prieſt told them.) At laſt I got a little Child into a corner, and opened his <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> which hung about his neck in a little ſilver caſe, ſhap'd lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and found nothing in it, but one grain of wheat wrapt in a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:19"/> Cotton, which had been hallowed by the Prieſt: but, if the true <hi>Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dei</hi> had not defended me, I had been mortally chaſtiſed for this, and other things, as burning Beads, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is impoſſible to write in what Veneration they have Saints Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and how many they have, as pieces of old hats, caps, gloves, ſhoes, boots, cords, garters, ſho-ſtings, coats, cloaks, points, laces, ſculs and other pieces, bits and fragments of their Bodies. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop <hi>Beck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> ſhoe was kept at
<hi>Harbledown</hi> near <hi>Canterbur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Hoſpital ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near the road, Where an old D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tard offer'd it to kiſs, to all Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, after they had been firſt beſprinkled with holy-Water.</p>
               <p>It is alſo as lamentable to think what Confidence they put in Images, which this one Story following may ſerve to evince, if there were no more (as there are thouſands) which ſome in <hi>London</hi> can teſtify to their Shame. <hi>For, ſome Town or City in</hi> Flanders <hi>(as I take it) being b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and fiercely aſſaulted by the Enemy without; in ſo much that all the people were in a terrible fright: which one of their Priests, or ſome other popiſh Votary perceiving, he got all the Keys of the City Gates, and in all haſte put them into the hands of an Image there, which was the Patroneſs of the Town: which having done,</hi> Now (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) there is no fear, for, I'le warrant you, ſhe'l defend the City from the Enemy, <hi>(or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rds to that effect) and yet the place was taken preſently after. And for all this, and a Thouſand other Deluſions, the blind and bewitch'd peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſtill mad upon their Idols</hi> (Jer. 50. 38.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is no marvel indeed, that they who rely ſo much upon Images, ſhould ſo little hope and confide in the true God. Nay, the Papists, (yea, and many papiſtical Proteſtants too) affirm,</hi> That no man can be ſure of Gods favour in this life: <hi>and their</hi> Tridentine
<hi>Council hath ſo defin'd: which Poſition is directly contrary to theſe Scriptures, (and which are too divine for thoſe</hi> Terrae fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii'<hi>s once to mention with their polluted lips.)</hi> Rom. 8. 15, 16, 17. Gal. 4. 6, 7. 2 Cor. 13. 5. 2 Tim 4. 8. Rev. 2. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Joh. 14. 22, 23, 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PRoceed we now to the pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh Synagogue at <hi>Swanſcomb,</hi> which was much haunted till
<hi>Henry</hi> the VIII time: for, to the Image of St. <hi>Hildeferth</hi> ſuch ran as were diſtracted, for reſtitution of their Wits, as faſt as men were wont to ſail to <hi>Anticyra,</hi> for <hi>Helleborus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Cure was perform'd here, by cloſe keeping, good diet, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit means, not only not ſtrange, or miraculous, but meer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, common and ordinary. And therefore, as on the one ſide, they <pb facs="tcp:36213:20"/> might truly be thought mad men that frequented this Pilgrimage: ſo on the other ſide, St.</hi> Hildeferth, <hi>of all the Saints that I know, might beſt be ſpared: Seeing the keeper of</hi> Bediam <hi>works mightily in the ſame kind of Miracles. However, if any happen'd to be cured, St.</hi> Hildeferth <hi>and his Image had all the praiſe, and the Prieſt all the profit. Thus the blind lead the blind into the Pit of Deſtruction,</hi> Mat.
15. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU have here in this S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Narration, an Account of the great and wonderful V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of Holy-water: eſpecially in frighting away the Devil, though he came to your bed-ſide, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you are, by night or by day: yea, if you do but ſhew him the Holy water pot it ſelf (if we believe Papiſts) he dares not come near it for his ears, but will pull in his horns, and ſneak away; and glad to eſcape ſo too.</p>
               <figure>
                  <p>† Reader, <hi>This Devil compleatly repreſents</hi> Strange, Cellier, <hi>the</hi> Compendium'<hi>s Aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r, &amp; all other that reproach the Proteſtant Religion, &amp; ſeem to put a Virtue upon the</hi> Popiſh.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>For, as they paſſed along in this gorgeous Aray, they uſed to have ſomebody dreſſed up like a Devil, who ſhould offer to invade or ſet upon the Company, and as though he would take the holy Croſs from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m: then out ſteped ſome bold fellow appointed for the purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, with the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water-pot in his hand, and with all his might flings holy water at him; at which this Counterfeit Devil muſt fearfully ſtart back f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r doubt of ſcalding, and tho many times he grind, and made as if he would fly in their Faces, yet might he never durſt be ſo bold indeed, as to approach, or come within the fall of any one drop of the holy water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus (forſooth) the Virtue of Holy-water in putting the Devil to ſlight, was confirm'd at <hi>Motinden</hi> by a demonſtrative Argument: Which, if it be ſo, then greatly was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> deceived, <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> chap. 6. where he would have us arm our ſelves <hi>Cap à Pe</hi> from the aſſaults of the Devil: for alas, what needed he to recite <hi>Sword, Shield, Helmet,</hi> and ſo many other parts of Defenſive and Offenſive Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, when the Holy-water ſtick alone would have ſerv'd the turn! or at leaſt, what meant he to omit it, being a thing ſo ſerviceable, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily provided? But we muſt give theſe blinde Popelings leave (after their wonted manner) to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Ghoſt to School. And yet, by the way, I muſt tell them, That they cannot <hi>Leonem larva terrere,</hi> ſcare a Lyon with a Vizard. It is not their <hi>Aqua lustralis,</hi> which they have fetch'd from <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Pot, and not from the Fountain of God's Word, that can make that roaring Lyon fly in good earneſt: nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let them beware this his Stratagem, and conſider, That even in worldly Warfare,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are never in more danger of the Enemy than when he feigneth to fly from them.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Majora canamus!</hi> Often, in <hi>Ireland,</hi> have I ſeen Papiſts go round the Verg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of their Corn-fields, and all to beſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inkle them with their Holy-water, to preſerve it (as they thought) from lightning and blaſting; and all to no purpoſe, for, I have obſerved, That when they <pb facs="tcp:36213:21"/> forbore their Holy-water, their Corn hath rather done better than when they beſprinkled it. They uſe the ſame Vanity in great thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning, for then they will beſprinkle their Sheep, Cows, Horſes, and all perſons preſent; and every womankind is to courtſey, and every mankind to pull
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff his hat and bow, when the water is flung at them, which, if any refuſe to do, (as Proteſtants have) they ſhall be ſure to be turn'd out of doors, or have a ſound cuff on the ear (or worſe) as I have had ſeveral. Yea many ſtrokes, ſtripes, and cruel whippings even at 7, 8, 9 and ten years of age, becauſe I would not go to Maſs (unknown to my Father) or bow to an Image: and for the ſame, my fleſh hath bin cut or lanced with Pen-knives, at the age above mentioned: ſo that at laſt, I was forc'd to fly for my life; and for that cauſe chiefly have I lived as a wandring Pilgrim in obſcurity, many years: in which time, I have endured a thouſand Miſeries, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch are the dire Concomitants of a voluntary Baniſhment: for they murdred my Brother, poiſon'd my Father, plunder'd &amp; burnt his houſe &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me with death, whereupon I fled the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XXI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TWO young Gentlemen of Royal Extraction, and own Brothers, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been murthered at a place called <hi>Eaſtry:</hi> the Archbiſhop of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> by any means, would needs have them buried at
<hi>Christ-Church</hi> in that City, intending to have them ſainted: whereupon he knew would undoubtedly follow, Pilgrimages, and Offerings, to the enriching of himſelf, and the Monks there (ſuch was the madneſs of People in thoſe dayes) but mark the ill luck he had in this his pious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention (pious Fraud, I ſhould ſay) for (ſaith the Tale-wright) when the Hearſe was ready, it would not be moved by any force towards that Church: as truly (ſaith one) as the Croſs of <hi>Waltham,</hi> with twelve ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and ſo many kine, could not be ſtirred any other way, but towards the place appointed: or, as the Image of <hi>Berecynthia,</hi> which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had brought out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> could not be removed till the Veſtal Virgin <hi>Claudia,</hi> had ſet her hand to it: but, to the premiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hereupon the Company aſſayed to convey it to S.</hi> Auguſtins: <hi>but all in vain: at the last, they agreed to have it to the Monastery of</hi> Watrine, <hi>and then (forſooth) it paſſed as lightly, as if nothing had been wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What horſe would not break his Bridle (as we ſay) at the hearing of this Prodigious Lie? or, who can forbear
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aughing, at this, and other ſuch deviſed Vanities? which, yet the blind Papiſts think a deadly ſin to queſtion the truth of, eſpecially when atteſted by a Monkiſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36213:21"/> as this is, as well as all the reſt. But theſe things were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by an unerring Author,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theſſ. 2. <hi>For the Miſtery of Iniquity doth already work. 7. And then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſs of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is Coming, 8. even him whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all Power, and Signs, and lying Wonders 9. and with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, in them that periſh; becauſe they received not the</hi> [love] <hi>of the Truth, that they may be ſaved 10. And for</hi> [this] <hi>cauſe (mark) GOD ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye 11: That they all might be Damn'd, who believe not the Truth, but had pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs 12. Now the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſſly, that in the lattter times, ſome ſhall depart from the Faith (mark) giving heed to ſeducing Spirits, and Doctine of Devils, speaking Lies in Hypocriſy, having their Conſcience ſeared with a hot Iron,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 12. <hi>Now as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moſes, ſo do theſe</hi> (Papiſts)
<hi>reſist the Truth, men of corrupt minds, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning the Faith:</hi> But they ſhall proceed no further, for their Folly ſhall be manifeſt to all men (to all true Proteſtants) as theirs alſo was 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8, 9.</p>
               <p>I make not doubt, but there are others beſides the Papiſts, concern'd in theſe Scriptures, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>England</hi> at this very day: for <hi>Antichrist</hi> is come forth into the World in ſeveral ſhapes: there are not only Wolves in Sheeps-clothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, but Foxes alſo in Lambskin. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for Satan himſelf is even now theſe preſent times, transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Light (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14.) in ſo much that <hi>if it were poſſible they ſhould deceive the very Elect,</hi> Matth. 24. 24. But many thouſands have been and ſhall be deceived, and are, even now, now, every day; though they do not ſee it, becauſe they do not believe, nor worſhip God aright, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XXII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT happened that the dead Corps of a man (loſt thro Shipwrack be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) was caſt on land in the Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh of <hi>Chatham,</hi> and being there taken up, was by ſome charitable people committed to honeſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urial in their Church and, which was no ſooner done, but our Lady of <hi>Chatham</hi> (as they ſtiled her, for her Image there was highly reverenced) finding herſelf offended therewith, aroſe by night (ſaith the Fable-Forger) and went in perſon to the Pariſh Clark's houſe, making a noiſe at's window, awak'd him; he, at the firſt, demanded ſomewhat roughly (for it ſeems he was in a profound ſleep) Who was there? but, when he underſtood <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36213:22"/> by her anſwer, that ſhe was the Lady of <hi>Chatham,</hi> he changed his note, and moſt mildly asked the Cauſe of her good Ladyſhips coming: ſhe told him, That there was lately buried near to the place where ſhe was worſhipped, a ſinful Perſon, which ſo offended her eye with his gaſtly grinning, That unleſs he were removed, ſhe could not but (to the great grief of all good people) withdraw her ſelf from that place, and ceaſe her wonted working Miracles among them: And therefore ſhe willed him to go with her, to the end that, by his help, ſhe might take him up, and throw him again into the Water.</p>
               <p>The Clark obeyed, aroſe, and waited on her towards the Church: but the good Lady (ſaith the Reporter) not wonted to walk, waxed weary, and therefore was enforced, for very want of breath, to ſit down in a Buſh by the way, and there to reſt her; and this Place (forſooth) as alſo the whole Track of their Journey, remained ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a green path.</p>
               <p>Now, after a while, they go forward again, and coming to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, digg'd up the Body, and carryed it to the water-ſide where it was firſt found.</p>
               <p>This done, the Lady Shrunk again into her Shrine, and the Clark peak'd home to patch up his his broken Sleep: but the Corps again floated up and down the River, as it did before, which they of <hi>Gilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> perceiving, it was once more taken up, and buried in their Church yard. But ſee what follow'd upon it! for not only the Rood of <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingham</hi> (ſay they) that a while before was buſy in working Miracles, was now deprived of all his former virtue, but alſo the very Earth and place where this Carcaſe was laid, did continually ſink downwards.</p>
               <p>This Tale, received by <hi>Tradition</hi> from the Elders, was (long ſince) commonly reported, and faithfully believed of the Vulgar ſort: for what Abſurdity is that they will not credit!</p>
               <p>But here (ſaith my Author) if I might make bold to add to this Fable, I would tell you, That I think the Moral and Meaning of the Tale to be none other, but that this Fabulator, being either the Farmer, Prieſt or owner of the Offerings, given to the Lady of <hi>Chatham,</hi> and envying the Common Haunt and Pilgrimage to the Rood of <hi>Gillingham</hi> (lately erected to his loſs) deviſed this Apparition for the Advancement of the firſt, and defacing of the ſecond.</p>
               <p>If that Age had been as prudent in trying Spirits, as it was prone to believe Deluſions, it ſhould have found, That our Ladyes path (afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) was ſome ſuch green trace of graſs, as we dayly ſee in the fields, proceeding indeed from a natural Cauſe; though by old wives, and
<pb facs="tcp:36213:22"/> ſuperſtitious people, reckoned to be the dancing places of Night-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which they call <hi>Fairies.</hi> And that this ſinking of the Earth, was nothing elſe but a falſe fill'd Pit, of the Clarks own digging. Since then, the whole Religion of <hi>Papistry</hi> it ſelf, is
<hi>Theomachia,</hi> and nothing elſe, and that is, <hi>A reſisting of God:</hi> Who but the <hi>Worſt</hi> of the worſt of Mankind, <hi>blind Sots, Atheiſts, Ruffians, Ranters, Robbers, Rogues, Whores, and Theives</hi> will own Popery, or dare hope to have it introduced either by Fawns or Frowns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="delusion">
               <head>Deluſion <hi>XXIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COME we next to <hi>Boxly Abby,</hi> which I had almoſt forgot, but by no means would ſo do, leſt the Favorers of falſe Religion might rejoyce at the Omiſſion, and the Followers of God's Truth juſtly cry out upon me; becauſe much of their popiſh Myſteries, preſtigious jugglings, and deluding Practices are inveloped in this one Story: and with which I reſolve to conclude, not for want of matter, but becauſe I think the aforementioned Relations ſufficient (if there were nothing elſe) to detect and evince the ſalſneſs, baſeneſs and odiouſneſs of the Romiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>In the daies of <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> it was freſh in the minds of both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts, and ſhall (I doubt not) to the profit of the one, be continued in perpetual Memory to all Poſterity) by what Myſtical Impoſture, Fraud, Juggling, and Legerdemain the ſilly People were ſeduced by the crafty Foxes of this Abby. The manner whereof I will ſed down in ſuch ſort only, as the ſame was ſometime by themſelves publiſhed in print, (for their Eſtimation and Credit, as they thought:) but, ſay I, to their own everlaſting Reproach, Shame and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It chanced on a time, That an Engliſh Carpenter was taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Wars betwixt</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France, <hi>who (wanting otherwiſe to pay for his Ranſom) thought with himſelf, having leiſure enough, to deviſe ſome curious piece of work to make Money thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, getting together fit Mater, he compacted of Wood, Wyer, Paste, and Paper, a Rood of ſuch exquiſite Art and Excellency, that it it not only match'd in Comlineſs, and due proportion of Parts, the best of the Common ſort, but in ſtrange Motion, Variety of Geſture, and nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joynts, paſſed all other that before had been ſeen; for it could bow down, and lift up it ſelf: Shake and stir the hands and feet, nod the head, roll the eyes, wag the chaps: bend the brows,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>ſo that now it needed not</hi> Prometheus <hi>fire to make it a lively man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but only the help of <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36213:23"/> the eovetous Priests of</hi> Baal, <hi>or the Aid of ſome crafty Colledge of Monks to deify, and make it paſs for a very God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This done, he made a Shift for his Liberty, came into
<hi>England</hi> on purpoſe to utter his Merchandiſe; and laid the Image upon the back of a poor Jade he drave before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now, when he was come as far as</hi> Rocheſter, <hi>he stept into an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe to drink, ſuffering his horſe to go forward alone: he was no ſooner out of his Masters ſight, but miſſing the ſtraight Western Road, which his Master intended to have gone, and turning South, trotted away to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> Boxly; <hi>and being driven, as it were, by ſome divine Fury, never ceaſed till he came to the Abby door, which he ſo beat and bounced at with his heels, that divers of the Monks hearing the noiſe, came to the place to know the matter, and wondring at the ſtrangeneſs of the thing, called the Abbot and his convent to behold it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Monks ſeeing the horſe ſo earneſt, and diſcerning what he had on his back, for doubt of deadly Impiety, opened the door, which they had no ſooner done, but the horſe ruſhed in, and ran in great haſte to a pillar (which was the very place where this Image was afterwards ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced) and there ſtop'd himſelf and ſtood ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now while thoſe D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſciples of Anti-Christ, the Monks, were buſy in taking off the Load, in comes the Carpenter, who by great inquiry had followed, and challenged his own: But the Monks, loath to looſe ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial a Stray, at firſt made ſome Denyal: but at last, being aſſured that he was the very Proprietor, they granted him leave to take it with him: Whereupon the Carpenter taketh his horſe by the head, to lead him out of the Abby, but he would not stir, then he strikes him, but the Jade was ſo resty, and fast nailed, that he would not once remove from the Pillar; at last, he takes off the Image, thinking to have carried it out by it ſelf, and then lead his horſe after it; but that alſo cleaved ſo fast to the ground, that notwithstanding all that ever he could do, it would not be moved one inch</hi> (ſaith the popiſh Author) cretenſe mendacium; <hi>ſo that in the end, partly through wearineſs, and by perſwaſion of the Monks, who were all in love with the Picture, and made him believe, That it was by God himſelf (blaſphemous Wretches) destinate to their houſe: he was contented for a piece of Money, to leave the Image behind him: which the Monks christned,</hi> The Rood of Grace.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the Generation of the great God of
<hi>Boxly,</hi> compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Creation of that beaſtly Idol of
<hi>Lampſacus,</hi> of which the Poet ſaith,</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36213:23"/>
                  <l>—<hi>Olim truncus eram ficulnus, inutile lignum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cum faber incertus ſcamnum, facerente Priapum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maluit eſſe Deum,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>—A Log unmeet for uſe,</l>
                  <l>Till Carver doubting with himſelf</l>
                  <l>wer't beſt make <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>apus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or elſe a Bench? reſolv'd at laſt</l>
                  <l>to make a God of me:</l>
                  <l>Thenceforth a God I am, of Bird</l>
                  <l>and Thieves moſt dread, you ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="sup">T</hi>his of the Poet agreeth with the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> viz. <hi>The Carpenter ſtretcheth out his rule, he marks it out with a line, he fitteth it with planes, and he marketh it out with a Compaſs, he maketh it after the figure of a man, according to the Beauty of a man, that it may remain in the houſe: He beweth him down Cedars, and taketh the Cypreſs and the Oak,—He burneth part thereof in the fire,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the reſidue thereof he maketh a God, even a graven Image, he falleth down to it, and worſhippeth it, and prayeth unto it, &amp; ſaith, Deliver me, for thou art my god,</hi> Iſa, 44. 12, 17. Again, <hi>They laviſh Gold out of the Bag, and weigh Silver in the Balance, and hire a Gold ſmith, and he maketh it a God, they fall down, yea, they woſhip, they bear him upon their ſhoulder, they carry him, and ſet him in his place, and he ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, from his place ſhall he not remove, yea, one ſhall cry unto him, yet can he not anſwer, nor ſave him out of his Trouble,</hi> Iſa. 46. 6, 7.</p>
               <p>And all this contrary to the expreſs Command of God. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, or in the Water under the Earth, thou ſhalt not bow down thy ſelf to them, nor worſhip them,</hi> Ex. 20. 3, 4, 5. ſo then, it is very plain, that in the multitude of gods, and in the manner of Woſhip, the Papiſts may well be compared with the old Heathens, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h they follow their rules, and examples, and not the Rule of Gods word. And therefore they may be ſaid to be the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Curſe; for it is written (and I am ſure it points at them as much as any) <hi>Curſed be the man that maketh</hi> (or cauſeth to be made) <hi>any graven, or molten Image, an abomination to the Lord, the work of the hand of the Crafts man, and putteth it in a ſecret place, and all the People ſhall ſay, Amen.</hi> Deut. 27.
15.</p>
               <p>But the Papiſts do not only worſhip Images in ſecret Places, but in publick alſo; whereby they openly declare themſelves to be the very Enemies of Chriſt, and the real Friends and Followers of
<hi>Anti-Chriſt?</hi> 
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36213:24"/> for do they not receive, and carry about them his mark, not only pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately in their right hand, but alſo moſt conſpicuouſly in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: <hi>ergo.</hi> Rev. 13. 16. 17.</p>
               <p>Now let us return to <hi>Boxley,</hi> from whence we have a little digreſſed.</p>
               <p>It cannot be fully declared how lewdly the Monks of that place, to their own inriching, and robbing of the blind people, abuſed this their wooden God, after they had thus gotten him: and which, by the juſt Judgment of the true God, was by that worthy Patriot, and zealous Proteſtant, the Lord
<hi>Cromwell,</hi> and pious <hi>Cranmer,</hi> pulled down, as well as the Abby, and the Monks quite diſperſed, in the Reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. And the whole Cheat laid open.</p>
               <p>But now, if I ſhould thus leave <hi>Boxley,</hi> the Papiſts would laugh in their ſleeves at my remiſneſs; for indeed the Cream of the Jeſt, (as we ſay) and the grand Cheats and Jugglings are ſtill behind, and therefore I pray attend; for I doubt not but to make you ſmile, before I have done.</p>
               <p>You muſt know, That beſides this (<hi>ungracious) Rood of Grace,</hi> as the Monks ſtiled it, they had alſo another Image, which was much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſame Place, called St. <hi>Rumbald,</hi> or, as others, St. <hi>Grumbald;</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>refore, I muſt ſpend a little time in the Detection thereof, as well for that it was as very a Deluſion as the former; as alſo for that the uſe of them both was ſo link'd together, that the one cannot well be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood without the other.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="examination">
                           <head>And this was the Manner.</head>
                           <p>If you intended to have any benefit by the <hi>Rood of Grace,</hi> ſo called, You muſt first be ſhriven, of one of the Monks,
<hi>i. e. you muſt confeſs all you ſins to him, and be forgiven:</hi> then by lifting at the Image of St. <hi>Grumbal,</hi> you muſt make Proof whether you were in clean life, or no: <hi>i. e. if you had not left ſome ſins unconfeſſed:</hi> and, if you were in clean life, then was your way prepared, and your Offering accepted of the Rood: if not, then you muſt be confeſſed anew, for it was to be ſuppoſed that you had concealed ſomewhat from your Ghoſtly DAD, and therefore, not yet worthy to be admitted <hi>Ad ſacra Eleuſina.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Now, that you may know how this Examination was to be made, you muſt underſtand that this <hi>Grumbal,</hi> or <hi>Rumbal,</hi> was a pretty. Saintling, or the Picture of a Boy-ſaint of Stone, ſtanding in the ſame Abby; of it ſelf ſhort, and not ſeeming to be heavy: but for as much as it was wrought out of a huge weighty ſtone, (being the baſe therof) it was hardly to be lifted by the ſtrongeſt man that was; nevertheleſs (ſuch was the crafty Conveyance) that by the help of an Engin, fixed to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36213:24"/> back thereof, it was eaſily raiſed up with the foot of him that was the Keeper, and therefore of no moment at all in the hands of ſuch as offered largely; and contrarywiſe, by the means of a pin running into a Poſt (which that Religious Impoſtor ſtanding out of ſight, could put in and pull out at pleaſure:) to ſuch as offred faintly, it was ſo faſt and unmoveable, that no force of hand could ſtir it, inſomuch as many times it cauſed much ſaughter, to behold a great Lubber lifting at that in vain, which a little Boy or Wench had eaſily taken up before him, becauſe they offred more frankly than he did.</p>
               <p>I omit how many chaſt Virgins and married Wives went often a way with bluſhing Faces, leaving (without cauſe) in the minds of the lookers on, great ſuſpicion of unclean Life, and wanton behaviour; for fear of which ſcandalous note, women (of all others) ſtretchd their Purſe-ſtrings, and ſought, by liberal Offerings to make St.
<hi>Crumbals</hi> man their good friend and favourer, by which, Whores alſo came off with as much credit as honeſt Women. <hi>O! The Deceits of</hi> Popery!</p>
               <p>But marke, (I beſeech you) their Monkiſh craft and pollicy in picking peoples Purſes, (for it was no better.) It was in vain (as the Monks perſwaded) to preſume to the <hi>Rood</hi> without ſhrift; yea, and Money loſt there alſo, if you offered before you were in clean Life: as they call it: and therefore the matter was ſo ordered, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trebble Offrings, <hi>viz. firſt,</hi> to the Confeſſor; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> to St. <hi>Grumbal; thirdly,</hi> to the Rood of Grace; the Pilgrims could not aſſure themſelves of any good gained by all their coſt and labour. I cannot conjecture (ſaith my Author) what Reaſon mov'd them to make this St.
<hi>Rumwald</hi> (or <hi>Grumbal</hi>) the Touch-ſtone of clean Life and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, unleſs it be upon occaſion of a Miracle that he did, in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Prieſts (<hi>now look for a whisker</hi>) to lift a great ſtone eaſily, which before, diverſe Lay-perſons (that is, prophane, as they will have it) could not ſtir with all their ſtrength: which thing (as alſo his Life and Death) to the end that the Tale ſhall want no part of due Credit, I will briefly recite, as in the Work (called <hi>Nova Legenda Angliae) John Capgrave</hi> hath Reported.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Pagan Prince of</hi> Northumberland, <hi>had married a Chriſtian Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (if a</hi> Papiſt <hi>be a Chriſtian) Daughter to the King of</hi> Mercia, <hi>or</hi> Mid-England, <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by no means would bed with her Husband, till he left his Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ry (and took up another as had) and become a Christian: at last he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſents, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> grows big with Child, and as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y were in their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; to viſit her Father, ſhe unexſpectedly falls in labour, and as ſoon as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36213:25"/> ever the Child was born (being a Son) he cryed out with a loud voice, three ſeveral times,</hi> Chriſtianus ſum, &amp;<hi>c. I am a Chriſtian, I am a Chriſtian, I am a Chriſtian; and ſo made profeſſion of his Faith, deſired to be Baptized, and with his Finger directed the ſtanders by, to fetch him a great hollow ſtone which he would have for his Font.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hereupon ſundry of the Kings Servants, aſſayed to have brought the Some, but it was ſo far above their ſtrength, that they could not once move it: which, when</hi> Rumbaldus <hi>perceived, he commanded the two Prieſts, (his appointed Godfathers) to go and bring i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which (ſaith the Legend) they did forthwith moſt eaſily (by virtue of their Holineſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) this done, he was Baptized, and within three days after his Spirit departed out of his Body, and was by the hand of Angels conveyed to Heaven: But before his Tranſlation, he diſcourſed cunningly (as St.</hi> Anthonies <hi>Pigg no doubt) of ſundry Popiſh Myſteryes, and bequeathed his Body to remain one year at</hi> Sutton, <hi>two at</hi> Brackley, <hi>and for ever at</hi> Buckingham.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Statius P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pinius</hi> a Poet, that lived in the Reign of <hi>Domitian,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were a Pagan or a Chriſtian, I know not; however, more Chriſtian than any Papiſt, whom he ſeems to Reprove, and point at as well as Heathen Idolaters, in this following Verſe. <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bais.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nulla autem effigies, nulli commiſſa metall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Forma Dei, mentis habitare &amp; pector a gaudet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gods form by Pictures cannot be expreſs't,</l>
                     <l>He loves to dwell within the Heart and Breaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Here you have had (<hi>Reader</hi>) above twenty <hi>Popiſh Deluſions, Falſe Miracles,</hi> and <hi>Lying Wonders</hi> laid open, and that but in ſome places of one County; by which you may gueſs what was in the reſt of <hi>England;</hi> nay, in all <hi>Europe,</hi> whoſe Superſtitions and Idolatries were infinite, whereby the blind People of thoſe dark Times were moſt miſerably, nay willingly fooled, couzened and cheated of their Monys, Houſes, Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and of their Witts too) and alſo abuſed, blinded, deluded and ruined in their Eternal Eſtates. And all the Premiſes are ſtill carried on, by the Twelve grand Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Antichriſt: and they are <hi>Popes Cardina's, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>triarchs, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, Officials, Abbots, Cannons, Monks, Fryers, Jeſuits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36213:25"/>Theſe laſt, being the very Life and Soul, the preſerver, maintainer, upholder and protector; yea, the very Chariots and Horſemen of the POPE, and the great Bulwark of Papiſtry; that he ſeſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) could better be without his right Eye, or his right Hand, than without them: for, they are indeed his right Hand, his Battle-Axes, his Rock, his Refuge, his <hi>Achitophel,</hi> his Tower, and (under his Lord
<hi>Lucifer</hi>) his grand <hi>Fulcrum,</hi> or prop and ſtay: for I am almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, were it not for that Politick Order, there had been no
<hi>Pope</hi> at this day; or if there were, it had been only <hi>in titulo,</hi> not <hi>in exercito.</hi> But one chief reaſon of the continuance of both, is the Sins of all the <hi>Species</hi> of Proteſtants, in General: together with the Impurities in Doctrine, or Errors in Judgment and Diſcipline, amongſt others of them: (from whence ſprang all our dire Diviſions and Diſſentions) I ſhall name none, the ſound Chriſtian knows who, which, and what I mean.</p>
               <q>Now, foraſmuch as the whole World of Papiſts, are already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all the Differences and Diſſentions that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Proteſtants; I ſhall therefore make the ignorant Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants (the Learned ſort knowing it without me) acquainted with a few of the Diviſions and Diſſentions amongſt even the grand Papiſts: for-all their ſeeming Unity: I ſay a few, for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to recite the one half of what I have read and heard, (to ſay nothing of what others know) and if I could, yet I have not room enough, for I reſolved when I began this Work not to exceed my bounds, of ſo many ſheets of Paper: Therefore I muſt perforce omit two thirds of what might be expoſed.</q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36213:26"/>
            <head>Popish DIVISIONS. OR, Their Diſſentions amongſt themſelves, <hi>Even in Fundamental Points.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Wherein you'l find <hi>Pope</hi> againſt <hi>Pope, Council</hi> againſt <hi>Council, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> againſt <hi>Cardinal, Biſhop</hi> againſt <hi>Biſhop, Prieſt</hi> againſt <hi>Prieſt, Jeſuite</hi> againſt <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="division">
               <head>I. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEllarminus</hi> and others affirm (<hi>l. 1. de cler. cap.</hi> 19.) that Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ought not to Marry; but their Cannon Law tells us, They may, <hi>diſt. 56. cap.</hi> where it is thus written, <hi>Cum ergo ex ſacerdotibus nati in ſummes pontifices ſupra legantur eſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moti,</hi> &amp;c. when therefore we read, that they were promoted to the Popedom, who were the Sons of Prieſts, we muſt not underſtand them to be Baſtards, but born in lawful wedlock: which Marriages were lawful for Prieſts, before the Pope: and they are held to be lawful in the Eaſtern Churches to this day. So that Papiſts will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm any thing, though againſt their own Laws, and the Laws of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3 and in the ſaid Cannons you ſhall find, That many Popes that there were Prieſts Sons, as, <hi>Felix, Deuſdedit, Agapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Bonifacius, Sylverius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> Here have you ſome Popes and their Clergy and Cannons for Prieſts Marriage: and other very hot againſt them! Why then, O ye Papiſts, do you tell us of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions? when ye your ſelves are more divided, even in Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="division">
               <head>II. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NAvarrus,</hi> That great popiſh Canoniſt, ſaith, That Men are bound to confeſs only their great and Mortal Sins; and, that a man may confeſs ſome and conceal others. Whoſe words are theſe; <hi>Hoc Preceptum non includit Venialia, etiamſi mixta ſunt mortalibus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Quibus conſequens eſt poſſe quem ſi velit, confeſſo uno peceato veniali, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum <pb n="33" facs="tcp:36213:26"/> tacere.</hi> This Precept (ſayes he) doth not include Venial Sins, though they are mingled with mortal Sins. Whereupon it follows, That the Penitents may (if they will) confeſs one Venial and conceal another. (Vide <hi>Navar. c. 21. n. 34 in Enchir.</hi>) So by this Doctrine, any Papiſt may diſſemble in Confeſſion, deceive the prieſt, and yet not ſin at all.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Gerſon,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Paris,</hi> is againſt him, in theſe words, <hi>Omne peccatum pro quanto eſt offenſa Dei, &amp; contra legem ejus aternam, eſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſua ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ditione &amp; indignitate mortiferum, &amp;c.</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſin, in that 'tis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Offence againſt God, and his eternal Law, is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of its own condition and indignity, according to the rigour of Juſtice, and divider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us from the life of Glory. The Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God may juſtly puniſh every offence as well with eternal as temporal Death, therefore every ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is mortal of its own Nature. The aſſumption is deduced from this, for that no (ſuch) puniſhment is ſo evil as the Offence, becauſe every puniſhment and death it ſelf ought to be endured, rather than the leaſt ſin committed: Grant the contrary, ſin ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lawful, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be no ſin at all. <hi>Vide Gerſon. de vita Spirituali. lect. 1. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. circa medium.</hi> Thus
<hi>Gerſonus,</hi> whoſe judgment in this particular all ſound Proteſtents aſſent to.</p>
               <p>Concerning Venial Sins, I have heard my ſelf, not many years ſince ſeveral Papiſts hold with <hi>Navarre,</hi> and others with
<hi>Gerſon:</hi> pray tell me now, what gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ater Diviſion can there be among Proteſtants than this? nay, among the ſound ones there is not the leaſt difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this, for they all agree, that the leaſt Sin, of its own nature, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currs Damnation. Then ceaſe boaſting of your unity, O ye Papiſts, ſith ye are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> divided among your ſelves than the bulk of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants know of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who are alſo as ignorant of Diviſions amongſt the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> againſt <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and Pope <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> the III. pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſecutes the very name of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Body after buried, he commanded to be taken up and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ded; be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ides many other Popes which have been miſerably divided concerning which, read <hi>Platina</hi> and <hi>Caranza in ſumma Concil. fol.</hi> 354. and 355. Dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s other Popes have come to that Dignity ſome by the Sword, ſome by private Murther, and ſome by Magick Art: as <hi>Christopher</hi> I.
<hi>Boniface</hi> VII. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> II: <hi>Damaſus</hi> II<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall conclude this, with the Epitaph of Pope
<hi>Benedict</hi> the XII<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> made by one of his own Clergy, by which you may ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what kind of men moſt of them were.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36213:27"/>
                  <l>Hic ſcitus eſt Nero, laicis mors viper a clero,</l>
                  <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vius à vero, cupa repleta mero.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>That is,</head>
                  <l>Here's <hi>Nero</hi> laid, to Lay-men was a Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>To Clergy-men a Viper void of Faith.</l>
                  <l>His Heart a wanderer from all Truth Divine,</l>
                  <l>His Head a Cup fill'd up with ſtrongeſt Wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Platina</hi> calls Pope <hi>John</hi> the XVIII<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Thief, a Robber: and <hi>Caran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za (in ſummo conciliorum</hi> fol. 369.) that great Thomiſt, thus painteth <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Intravit ut Vulpes, regnavit ut Lupus, mortus eſt ut Canis, i. e.</hi> He entred as a Fox, He reigned as a Woof, He dyed as a Dog.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="division">
               <head>III. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Pope, Cardinals and Jeſuites affirms, that Infidels, are not bound to their Auricular Confeſſion: But <hi>Angelus, Richardus,</hi> and <hi>Gabriel</hi> hold the contrary. <hi>See Joſ. Engles. in 4. S. ar. 2. de confeſſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now concerning Auricular Confeſſion, papiſts differ among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and that it was never commanded by Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, as their own Doctors out of their own Canon Law teſtify; of which thus writeth <hi>Sylveſter Prieras. de confeſ. ſecundo. par. 4. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum ad Confeſſionem teneamur divino jure vel humano?</hi> &amp;c It is demanded
<hi>ſaith he,</hi> whether we are bound to this Confeſſion, by the Law of God or man? I ſay, that the Canoniſts hold, that we are but bound by the Law of Man. And the <hi>Popes</hi> own Decrees ſay no leſs in theſe words: <hi>Quibus authoritatibus, vel quibus rationum firmamentis utra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſententia ſatisfactionis &amp; confeſſionis nitatur,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>vide de poe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. d. 1. cap. quamvis) viz.</hi> upon what Authority or Reaſons either O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is grounded, is ſhewed before. Now to which of them the Reader ſhould adhere, I leave it to his own diſcretion, for either O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion (pray mark) hath wiſe and Religious men, that averr the ſame.</p>
               <p>Obſerve (good Reader) that not only the <hi>Popes</hi> own Doctors, but his own Law, and the Commentators thereon, acknowledge that <hi>Au icular Confeſſion</hi> is grounded only upon Humane Laws, and take notice their own Gloſs tells you, that Wiſe and Religious men hold, ſome for, and ſome againſt it. O the rare Unity of the Church of <hi>Dome!</hi> if Diſcordancy and Repugnancy be Unity?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="division">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:36213:27"/>
               <head>IV. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NAvarrus</hi> and the Jeſuits teach, that a man may both deny in word and upon his Oath, that which the Judg demandeth of him; ſo he equivocate and make his own ſence to himſelf, (<hi>Navar. in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir. c.
18. n</hi> 61. and <hi>cap. 25. n.</hi> 43.) But Dr. <hi>Sepulveda,</hi> is utterly againſt it: yea, the Jeſuits will ſometimes by equivocation, and mental reſervation deny themſelves to be Chriſtians, as their own Brother
<hi>John Muſh</hi> confeſſed, in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time: and if ſo, as no doubt but it is: Then what heed can be giv'n to the ſeveral Plea's and dying ſpeeches of <hi>Harcourt, Whit: bread, &amp;c.</hi> when they took it upon their Salvation, that they were as Innocent of all that was laid to their charge, <hi>as the Child unborn:</hi> and though many fooliſh people ignorant of the depths, quaerks, quacks, knacks, tricks, illuſions and curious Arts of Jeſuites and Jeſuitiſm, poſſibly may have been amuſed, ſtartled and ſtagger'd at the ſerious, ſolemn and dying aſſeverations, and deep proteſtations of the ſaid <hi>Harcourt, Whitebread,</hi> and the reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet for my own part, I do no more value their words, their dying words, than I do the chattering of a <hi>Mag-Pye,</hi> or the tears of a <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile;</hi> for, if people knew their Principles, their cantings, quaerks, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> as well as I do, they would abhorr them for the verrieſt wretches, and meareſt miſcreants in point of mental reſervation, and equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ever the Earth bore: for I have been acquainted with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them in my time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="division">
               <head>V. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <p>
                     <hi>AQuinas, Bellarminus,</hi> &amp;c. affirm Matrimony to be a Sacrament; but <hi>Durandus</hi> is againſt them, denying (as they affirm) that it neither conferreth Grace, no: is properly a Sacrament (<hi>Durand. in
4. diſt. 26 qu.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) and with him held <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro,</hi> and <hi>Petrus à Sot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, (apud Bellar. l. 1. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> matri.</hi> c. 6.)</p>
                  <p>And their Biſhop <hi>Mel. Canus,</hi> perceiving ſuch difference in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning this matter, that he counts him a mad man that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves any of them: His words are theſe:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lege Magiſtrum</hi> (Aquinum) Scotum, Richard. Bonaven. Durand. <hi>cateroſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Schol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Theologos, &amp; niſi ſtatim corum pendentes at vacillantes animos deprehenderis, tum vero me aut ſtultum, aut temerarium judicato,</hi> &amp;c. can. de locis. l. 8. cap. 5. p. 245.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36213:28"/>
                  <head>Thus Engliſhed.</head>
                  <p>Read the Maſter (<hi>Aquinas) Bouadventure, Richardus Paludanus, Durandus,</hi> &amp;c. and if thou doſt not perceive their wavering and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minds, then (ſaith he) judge me either a fool or a raſh fellow: for when they enquire if Matrimony conferr Grace; that which was eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be Defin'd, that, Define they not at all, but only tell us what others think thereof: alſo in determining the matter and form of this Sacrament, they are ſo unconſtant and various (mark) ſo uncertain and ambiguous that he may be judged a fool, whom in ſuch Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will eſtabliſh any conſtant Doctrines. <hi>Here the Proteſtant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may ſee Papiſts diſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing, even about their Sacraments, &amp; moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant matters.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="division">
               <head>VI. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAnormitanus, Almainus, Cuſanus, Gerſonus, Abulenſis,</hi> with the whole Council of <hi>Conſtans,</hi> affirm, every General Council to be above the Pope, (as I can prove more largely, had I room enough) But all the <hi>Dominicans, Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Seminaries</hi> do with open mouth thunder out the contrary, as their Writings, and Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="division">
               <head>VII. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gustinus de ancona,</hi> and <hi>Sylveſter Prieras (de Papa. num.</hi> 10. and 14.) hold, that the Pope doth more excel the Emperor in Dignity, than Gold doth Lead. But <hi>Bellarmine (l. 4. de Rom. Pont. c.</hi>
1.) and <hi>Fra. Victoria (reſt. eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 38.) ſharply impugne their Opinion.—<hi>Igitur ſummus Pontifex</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine) ut Chriſti Vicarius, atque adeo ut ſummus Pontifex eſt, inullum habet temporale Dominium. i. e.</hi> Therefore the Pope as Chriſts Vicar, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Pope, hath no Temporal Dominion. And ſaith
<hi>Victorian,</hi> in the fore-quoted place. <hi>Poteſtas temporalis non dependet à ſummo Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>out aliae poteſtates ſpirituales inferiores, &amp; paulo poſt, Licet aſſerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res alterius partis commuinter dicunt, quod papa inſtituit omnem poteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem temporalem,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Sed totum hoc, est fictitium, &amp; ſine que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que probabilitate, nec innit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur velratione, vel teſtimonijs, vel Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, vel ſaltem alicujus ex puribus, vel vere Theologis, ſed gloſſatores juris hoc Dominum dederunt Papae, cum ipſi eſſent pauperes rebus &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctrina.</hi> Temporal power (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) and he ſaith true, doth not depend upon the Pope, as inferior Spiritual powers do: although others on the other part, commonly ſay, that the Pope Ordained all Tempora power, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>—But all this is a meer Fable, and void of all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36213:28"/> neither hath it any ground, either of reaſon or Scripture, or Ancient Fathers, or good Divines; yet the Gloſſers of the Canons (<hi>mark</hi>) gave the Pope this preheminence, becauſe themſelves were beggarly fellows and unlearned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold here the Original of Papacy, whereof Ignorance and Poverty were the Advancers; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d that by the Teſtimony of this moſt learned Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> With whom holds</hi> Bellarmin.
<hi>Obrave <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity! if Diſunion be it!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="division">
               <head>VIII. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny great Papiſts, <hi>viz. Marſilius, Richardus, Paludanus, Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> with all his Canoniſts affirm, That a Prieſt by Vertue of the Popes Diſpenſation, may lawfully and effectually miniſter their Sacrament of confirmation. See
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Joſ. Angleſ.</hi> upon that Subject. And
<hi>Covarruvias Tom. 2. l. 1. c. 10. p. 24. de ſacra confirmatione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe are hotly impugned by <hi>John Maior, Bonavent. Alpho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus, Scotus, Durandus,</hi> and Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> ſaying, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> was a Man, and therefore ſubject to err.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See here, what greater diſſention can be than this? for Confirmation is one of their ſeven Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="division">
               <head>IX. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOnaventura, Jo. Maior, Aquinas, Albertus Magnus, Almainus, Richardus,</hi> &amp;c. firmly hold, that every of their Seven Orders is a Sacrament (<hi>vide Bellarmine, Joſ. Angles,</hi>) But <hi>Durandus, Petrus Lombardus, Gajetanus, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctoris</hi> and <hi>Joſ. Angles,</hi> hold the contrary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>vide Jo. Angles de ſacr. ord. art. 2. diſtic. 3. &amp; victoria. de poteſt. eccleſ. relect. 2. p. 90. &amp; de Sacramento, ord. p.</hi>
119.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="division">
               <head>X. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Pope and his Jeſuits affirm, that the Virgin
<hi>Mary,</hi> was conceived without Sin; but <hi>Aquinas</hi> and the Thomiſts ſtoutly defend the contrary Opinion. <hi>Aquin. 1. n. 3. part. 9.
27. ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. ad</hi> 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="division">
               <head>XI. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Scotiſts</hi> avouch, that we can keep all the Commandements <hi>quoad ſubſtantiam operis.</hi> The Thomiſts ſay, we can keep ſome, but not all; but <hi>Gregorius</hi> their great Schoolman holds, That we can keep none. <hi>Short and Sweet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="division">
               <pb facs="tcp:36213:29"/>
               <head>XII. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Papiſts are miſerably divided concerning Venial Sins, which (ſay many of them) are no breach of the Law, becauſe they are not
<hi>contra legem,</hi> but <hi>praeter legem</hi> ſay they: but this Opinion is ſharply reproved by other Papiſts. <hi>vid. M. Baius. apud. Bellar. de. Purgat. l. 2. c. 4. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the year 1673. I was preſent at a diſpute upon this ſubject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Prieſt and a Papiſt Gentleman; the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> held Venial Sins, but the ſecond, not only denyed them, but utterly confuted the Prieſt, and all his partakers: but at laſt they grew ſo hot on both ſides, that they bent their Fiſts, and ſhook their Canes at one another. (Of this point:) ſee
<hi>Joſ. Angleſ. in 4. ſent. de ſacram. p.</hi> 219)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="division">
               <head>XIII. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>INcredible is the Diſſention among Papiſts, touching the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſubſtance, out of the accidents, which Papiſts imagine to remain without ſubjects in the Euchariſt: concerning which,
<hi>Richar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> holds one Opinion, <hi>Scotus</hi> another,
<hi>Cajetanus</hi> another, <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> another, <hi>Aquinas</hi> two, the one repugnant to the other. <hi>vid. Jo. Angl. in 4 art. ult de a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cid. euchar.</hi> Let not the Papiſts hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward boaſt of their Unity, nor charge the Proteſtants with diſſentions, for in truth, it is as much and more their own Badge, if all were known.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="division">
               <head>XIV. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth it as matter of Faith, to believe Chriſts Body to be in every part, when one of their Bread-Gods, or conſecrated Hoſts, is broken in pieces, but <hi>John Maior,</hi> their School Doctor, ſaith, it is a Probleme. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. Angl. in 4. Senn. 91. de euchar. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffic.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="division">
               <head>XV. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Johannes Pariſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſis</hi> affirmeth the ſubſtance of Bread to be united to the Body of Chriſt, Hypoſtatically: <hi>Durandus</hi> holds that the ſubſtance of Bread is deſtroyed, but the matter of Bread abideth ſtill with Chriſts Body <hi>Caje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anus</hi> ſaith, (and he ſaith true) that nothing in the Goſpel enforceth us to underſtand theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> ſo groſſly and carnally as the Papiſts do. The Council of
<hi>Trent</hi> teacheth, that the Bread is neither annihilated, neither abideth in the Sacrament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:36213:29"/> Sirs, who cannot but ſmile at theſe Abſurdities! For, if it be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Sacrament, or become nothing, I would know what it is, and where it abides. <hi>Vide Aquinas, p. 3. q. 65. ar. 4. apud Joſeph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleſ. in 4 Sent. de converſ. p.</hi>
166.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="division">
               <head>XVI. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is a great Queſtion, and breeds much Diſſention among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: What that is which a Mouſe eateth, when ſhe eateth their reſerved Hoſt? <hi>Peter Lombard, Bonaventure</hi> and others, affirm, That the Mouſe eateth not Chriſts Body: (and I am of their mind) But the Popes, Cardinals and Jeſuices, hold the contrary, as a groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Article of their Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Lombard and Bonavent. in 4. ſect. d.</hi> 13. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what rare Unity here is!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="division">
               <head>XVII <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Popiſh Clergy and their Tridentine Councel deny their Communicants the Cup, and give them only the Bread; nay, the ſaid Council curſe ſuch as affirm. That the people ſhould receive under both kinds. But their own Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> is againſt them, when he decreed as followeth. <hi>Comperimus, quod quidam ſumpta tantum modo corporis ſacriportione à ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> crueris a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtineant,</hi> &amp;c. (Vid. de conſ diſt.
2. cap. comperimus.) We underſtand (ſaith the Pope) that certain receiving the portion of Chriſts body, abſtain from the Cup: which men, (doubtleſs trained up in Superſtition) let them be forced either to receive the whole Sacrament, or be reſtrained from the whole; becauſe this dividing of the whole M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtery cannot be without great Sacri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dge—<hi>I pray n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w tell me, To which of theſe in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> great Diſſention among themſelves, in this great point, ſhould the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ople adh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re? for, if they follow the Councill, the Pope condemns them, if they obey the Pope, the Council curſeth them. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſe to twit Proteſtants with their Diviſions, ſince th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mſelves
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> divid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d more than we.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Papiſts are not only divided in their Expoſition of Scripture, but alſo very erroneous: eſpecially in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, they take the <hi>Sign</hi> for the thing ſignified: the Earthy for the Heavenly: The ſubſtance of bread, for the very body of Chriſt: the thing vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inviſible: the Kings picture (as I may ſay) for the Kings perſon. So that where they ſhould uſe a Trope or Figure in expounding, they ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k to the letter: and where they ſhould ſtick to the letter, there they fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce an Allegory. In theſe words of Chriſt <hi>Mat. 26. 26. This is my Body:</hi> They perverſly keep to the letter: <pb n="40" facs="tcp:36213:30"/> which being a figurative Speech, muſt be underſtood, <hi>This ſignifies my Body.</hi> But theſe Ideots, hand over head, muſt and will take the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, repreſentation, or figure of Chriſt in the Sacrament, for the real ſubſtance of his body, fleſh, blood and bones, in all its proportion as when he was nailed to the Croſs! O ye ſenſleſs bruits!</p>
               <p>The ancient Orthodox Writers (and divers Papiſts too) expound it ſacramentally, as we do. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his 2 &amp; 4 Book againſt <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> (whom <hi>Iraenaeus</hi> ſtiles <hi>Os Diaboli</hi>) renders it, <hi>figura corporis mei.</hi> Again, he ſaith,
<hi>Dominus, pane corpus ſuum repreſentat,</hi> The Lord repreſents his Body by bread. So ſaith <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Preface to the 3 Pſalm. And againſt <hi>Adanantius,</hi> you may thus read him; <hi>Non dubitavit Deminus dicere, Hoc eſt corpus meum, cum daret ſignum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porie fui,</hi> Chriſt doubted not to ſay, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> when he gave (<hi>mark</hi>) only a ſign of his Body. Again, <hi>Judam adhibuit ad convivium, in quo corporis &amp; ſanguinis ſui figuram commendavit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulis,</hi> Chriſt admitted Judas to his Supper, in which he commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Diſciples only the figure of his body, <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſam. 3. <hi>Judas</hi> only receiv'd the bread of the Lord, the Apoſtles receiv'd the bread and the Lord. And the ſame Author upon Pſam 50. touching the words of Chriſt, in <hi>John 653. Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, ye have no life. This</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) is underſtood very groſſly and carnally by many: as though Chriſt would cut away lumps and pieces of his body and give it them.</hi>—But they ſaid, <hi>v. 60. This is an hard ſaying; but they were</hi> (as the Papiſts are) <hi>hard of belief, and not the ſaying: for had they had true Faith th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> would have underſtood him ſpiritually: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in theſe words, and all other words of the ſame purpoſe, there lyeth hid a ſacramental meaning and mystery: which therefore must alwayes be underſtood spiritually, mystically, figuratively, tropically;</hi> and not popiſhly, groſly, carnally, or literally. And <hi>Auguſtin</hi> expounds this Text,
<hi>The Rock was Chriſt,</hi> thus, <hi>The</hi> Rock <hi>did ſignify</hi> Chriſt: See <hi>lib. 38. de Civit. Dei, cap.</hi> 38. for Chriſt was not a natural ſtone, tho he was the <hi>Stone</hi> figuratively. And ſo ſaith
<hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nrus, Solet res quae ſignificat nomine rei, quam ſignificat nominare,</hi> The thing which ſignifieth (ſaith this learned Papiſt) is wont to be cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the name of the thing which it doth ſignify: and ſo is the ſtone ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt,</hi> called Chriſt, when it is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed, but a figure of him:
<hi>Ergo,</hi> the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament is no more.</p>
               <p>This Expoſition is alſo confirmed by their own <hi>Bernard, in aſſ. mar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> per ſignificationem, non proprietatem,</hi> Chriſt is a ſtone by ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, not that he is properly ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:36213:30"/>The blind Popiſh Doctors, and all Papiſts (as well as the perverſe Scribes and Phariſees, and the ſtiffneck'd Jews,) are greatly miſtaken in their expoſition concerning the Words of Chriſt. <hi>John 6. 54. Who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternal Life.</hi> Now, theſe Words cannot be underſtood Sacramentally (in this place) as the Papiſts Dream; becauſe they were ſpoken before the inſtitution of the Sacrament: thus they Wreſt the Scriptures to their own Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Now, concerning the real Body of Chriſt in the Popiſh Sacrament, if they hold (as many of them do) that Chriſt is there without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions; their great Evangeliſt <hi>Aquinas</hi> is againſt them. (<hi>v. Aqu. p. 3. q. 76. art.</hi> 4.) but their laſt ſhift is this (from which they will not ſtir in Life and Death) viz. <hi>God can miraculouſly bring it ſo to paſs.</hi> Neither will this ſhift help them, for
<hi>ultra poſſe, non eſt eſſe:</hi> for in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wiſe men, yea, even their own School Doctors; there are ſome things which God cannot do, or rather which cannot poſſibly be done: For inſtance, <hi>God cannot Sin, God cannot make time paſt, not to be past; God cannot make that a Blind man remaining Blind, not want his ſight, though he can give ſight to the Blind: God cannot make that a Dead man remaining Dead, have Life, though he can reſtore Life to the Dead:</hi> in ſhort, <hi>God can do nothing that implyeth Contradiction:</hi> and all this Argues no Impotency in God, who is Omnipotent; but defect in the things themſelves, that ſhould be done. So then, <hi>this imaginary being of Chriſts whole Body in a little round Cake as big as a fix pence, is a flat contradiction, therefore cannot poſſibly be done.</hi> For, <hi>what pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er can bring to paſs, that a Body of ſix foot long, and two foot broad, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtill ſo long and ſo broad, ſhall be contained in another Body of three foot long, and one foot broad?</hi> Why this is the very Caſe of Chriſts Body in the Popiſh Cake. I could never yet meet with any Papiſts that could reſolve this: for indeed
'tis impoſſible. <hi>Ergo,</hi> their Doctrines, are moſt falſe, erroneus, blaſphemous, abſurd and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: For, what is more abſurd, than to hold, (as they do) <hi>That Chriſts real and whole Body is in a thouſand places at once, and at the ſame time chewed and ſwallowed down into the Stomach and Bellys of thouſands, and afterwards let fall into their houſes of Office!</hi> O, moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable Doctrine! O, moſt abominable Papiſts, and Papiſtry! Who but Fools, Mad-men and Rebrobates would be of your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion!</p>
               <p>Give me leave once more <hi>(good Reader)</hi> to touch upon ſome perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent paſſages before inſerted.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:31"/>Signs or Sacraments in Scripture, are called by the names of the things ſignify'd; or whereof they are Signs and Sacraments.</p>
               <p>Chriſt (as aforeſaid) is called <hi>a Stone, (Acts 4. 11.) A Vine, (John 15. 1.) A door. (John 10. 7.) A Shepherd, (Heb 13. 20. and John 10.
11.) and his Father a Husband man (John</hi> 15. 1.) is Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Stone indeed? a natural Vine? a material Door? a meer ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Shepherd? and is his Father a Country Farmer, Plough-man, or Husband-man? (for they are all one) muſt all theſe therefore be underſtood
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itterally?</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt is called <hi>a Star. (Numb. 24. 17.) a Branch, (J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 33. 15.)</hi> can any of theſe be expounded without a Trope or Figure? no more can the Body of Chriſt in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt called <hi>John Baptiſt, Elias (Mat.</hi> 11.
14.) is <hi>John</hi> therefore the very ſame <hi>Elias,</hi> in 1.
<hi>Kings</hi> 18? Chriſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iohn, the Son of Mary; and Mary, Iohn's Mother, (Iohn</hi> 19. 26, 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Was <hi>Iohn</hi> therefore the very natural Son of the <hi>Virgin Mary?</hi> and ſhe the true Mother of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn?</hi> I think there is no Papiſts ſo Mad as to affirm it: No more then, is the Sacramental Bread, Chriſts natural Body; though Chriſt called it his Body, that is, Figure of his Body.</p>
               <p>Indeed the Papiſts grant, that divers other Scriptures are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood Figuratively, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and ſome others muſt not: and why? becauſe the Pope hath ſo decreed, therefore they muſt (jump with the <hi>Collier) Believe as the Pope Believes; and obey his Commands before Chriſt and his Apoſtles:</hi> But thoſe that are true Worſhipers of God, are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t bound by the Law of God, to obey Popes, Princes, nor any Magiſtrates whatſoever, in matters of Religion, if they command contrary to the Scriptures. And, for this we have many preſidents, whereof I ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> here inſert ſome:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Godly Midwives would not obey</hi> Pharaoh
<hi>in killing innocent Children.</hi> Exod. 1. 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The three young Iſraelites refuſed to obey the Command of</hi> Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar, <hi>to worſhip the Golden Image.</hi> Dan. 3.
18.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Prophet</hi> Daniel <hi>refuſed to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y the ungodly decree of</hi> Darius. Dan. 6. 10, 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ithful</hi> Jews <hi>refuſed to obey the Law of</hi> Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, <hi>when he commanded them to Sacrifice to Idols.</hi> Vide Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cha, <hi>the Mother of King</hi> Aſa, <hi>Worſhiped Idols, as did many others, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that feared God abhorred her doings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36213:31"/>6. Jeroboam <hi>commanded Iſrael to Worſhip his Golden Calves: but the true Servants of God would not obey him.</hi> 1 Kings 12. 28.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Queen <hi>Jezebel</hi> worſhipped <hi>Baal, and commanded others to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſo: but all that feared the Lord utterly rejected her; whom ſhe Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and Murthered the Prophets of God:</hi> read <hi>Ahabs</hi> reign 1 <hi>Kings 16. 31. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Athaliah, <hi>a great Queen, was an Idolatreſs, and enticed her Son</hi> Ahaziah, <hi>and commanded others to the ſame Idolatry; but the faithful Servants of the Lord, obeyed neither the King nor his Mother in that matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>The Prieſts, Lawyers, Scribes, Phariſees, and Saduces, were great Rulers. And they commanded the Apoſtles to Preach no more in the name of Ieſus: but they obeyed them not.</hi> But ſtoutly anſwered, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to harken unto you, more than to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judge ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Acts 4. 19.</p>
               <p>Now, What became of all theſe perſecuting Kings and Queens?
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Subjects were Plagued, and afterwards periſhed in the red Sea. <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> convinced; and after puniſhed ſeven years for his Pride. <hi>Antiochus</hi> died miſerably. <hi>Maacha</hi> depoſed, and ſcorned. <hi>Iezebel</hi> eaten up of Dogs. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſlain. <hi>Iereboam</hi> puniſht in his poſterity. 1 <hi>Kings 14. 10. Athaliah</hi> was ſlain, for all her crying out, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon! 2 Kings 11. 14. 16. Herod,</hi> a great perſecutor, was eaten up of Worms.
<hi>Acts 12. The High Prieſts, Lawyers, Scribes, Phariſees</hi> and
<hi>Saduces,</hi> together with their chief City, and Temple, whole Country and people, were utterly, totally, and finally deſtroyed by the
<hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe I think, are ſufficient warnings to all Popes, Cardinals, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Princes and Magiſtrates of all degrees, that they impoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on their Subjects in matters of Religion, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Commands of God in his Word.</p>
               <p>To conclude, tell me, What has the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (to name no more) got by ſetting up, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d allowing the Bloody INQUISITION in his Dominions? Truly, he has never thrive ſince: has he not loſt ſeven of his ſeventeen <hi>Belgick Provinces,</hi> and a great part of the reſt to the <hi>French!</hi> Nay, has not the Pope himſelf loſt <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland, Denmark, Swedeland,</hi> a great part of <hi>Germany, France, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Switzerland, &amp;c.</hi> For his Cruelties, and Idolatrous impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of Religion? And particularly, that Saint-torturing, and Murthering engine,
<hi>viz.</hi> TRANSUBSTANTIATION, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Words, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> I cannot but grieve to find <pb n="44" facs="tcp:36213:32"/> how ignorant many Proteſtants are, and thoſe too, of good rank and quality, grave and ſerious, of refined parts, old profeſſors of both Sexes: ſeveral of whom, I have often ſeen at a loſs (to their ſhame be it ſpoken) and wofully non-plus't in diſcourſe with Papiſts, anſwering ſo weakly and childiſhly! yea, moſt ſhamefully baffled, and ſilenc't, even by Popiſh Children; to the great diſadvantage
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. (And all through their ſlothfulneſs, wordlineſs,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>) To prevent which miſchief among Papiſts, Prieſts, Fryers, and many Parents, in what Family ſoever they find an acute Boy or Girl, they teach them how to diſpute of ſome ſpecial points of Religion: the neglect whereof among Proteſtants is (in my Judgment) not only ſhameful but ſinful. And truly I could wiſh, that Miniſters in their publick Aſſemblies, would preach oftener than they have done upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.
26. and 16. 18. and 18. 18. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20 23. and ſuch like. With which your crafty Papiſts make a deal of ſtir in the company of ignorant Proteſtants. And I have often found, that they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe upon one of thoſe four Texts, and other ſuch, then any other Scriptures; which they will by many Tricks, ſhifts and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes labour to avoid. By which we may ſee, that Papiſts have more Zeal for Anti-Chriſt, than Proteſtants have for Chriſt! Nay, They have, do, and will with more cheerfulneſs, and willingneſs ſpend thouſands for their Catholick Cauſe, than thouſands called Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, will hundreds for the Cauſe of God! O COVETEOUS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS! Thou art become the Maſter-Devil amongſt us! Thou'lt bury thy Money, or keep it for the Papiſts, rather than employ part of it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſerve thy Life and Religion; as the
<hi>Conſtantinopolians</hi> did, when <hi>Mahomet</hi> &amp; his
<hi>Turks</hi> beſieged them; but after he took the City, and found their hidden Treaſure, he uttered this reproachful Taunt. <hi>viz. Behold! Here was Treaſure enough to have raiſed an Army, ſufficient to defend their City and Country from us!</hi> implying, <hi>That they loved their Mony better than their Live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Liberties and Religion!</hi> So, that through their <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> they loſt all at once, To their eternal ſhame and infamy, the great diſgrace of Chriſtian Religion, and diſhonour to Chriſt among Turks! So now, there are many wiſh well to the cauſe of Chriſt: but they will do little enough for it, either in purſe or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: they are godly for their own private good, if they have but grace ſufficient to carry them to Heaven, they care for no more, let the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſtant cauſe ſink or ſwim, and now it is in danger, they cry <hi>God help, God help,</hi> and thats all. O, what narrow ſpirited, and frozen hearted <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Laodiceans</hi> are theſe! <hi>Rev<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 4. 5. and</hi> 3. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="division">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36213:32"/>
               <head>XVIII. <hi>DIVISION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOST vehement are the exclamations of <hi>Catharinus</hi> againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetanus,</hi> and of <hi>Antonius Fontſecca,</hi> againſt
<hi>Catharinus,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the formation of <hi>EVE,</hi> as alſo
<hi>Burgenſis,</hi> againſt <hi>Lyranus,</hi> and <hi>M. Thoring</hi> againſt <hi>Burgenſis,</hi> in many other things, and all this will appear to ſuch as will peruſe their Gloſſes upon the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="division">
               <head>XIX. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>POpe <hi>Hadrian, Richardus,</hi> and <hi>Panormitanus,</hi> affirm, That a Prieſt being contrite: may ſay Maſs before he be confeſſed. But the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> is againſt it, as a damnable Sin. <hi>Ioſ. Angleſ. in 4. ſ. p.</hi> 117.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="division">
               <head>XX. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> (where a monſtrous OWL, the Emblem of the evil Spirit which guided them (as the Dove is of the good) appeared to the great amazement of the Pope and his <hi>Achitophels,</hi> defined abſolutely, that Angels were created with the World. But
<hi>Nazianzenus, Damaſcenus, Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius, Hieronimus, Auguſtinus,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> deny it to be a matter of Faith. <hi>Council. Lat. Can. 1. de ſide Cathol.</hi> and
<hi>Canuſ. de locis. lib. 5 p.</hi> 169.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="division">
               <head>XXI. <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEllarmin</hi> avoucheth, <hi>That the Major Voice in general Councils, muſt needs be of moſt force.</hi> But <hi>Canus</hi> holdeth, <hi>That the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nor part is the beſt, if the Pope hold with it.</hi> And yet in their agreement in this point, reſteth the Foundation of their Ropiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>But to what end are <hi>Councils,</hi> if the <hi>Pope</hi> hath a Negative Voice, and rule them as he pleaſeth: though abſent, for indeed, Popes have been very ſeldom preſent at <hi>General Councels;</hi> as
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> recordeth, <hi>Summus pontifex nunquam interfuit concilijs orientali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus per ſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Bellarmine lib. 1. de concilijs cap.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>The Pope (ſaith he) <hi>Was never preſent at the Councels in the East-Church in his own perſon.</hi> And why? Becauſe the Emperor Sate in higheſt place. Which the humble Pope could by no means endure, becauſe he would not ſit in the ſecond place: yet he ſtiles himſelf, <hi>Servus Serv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>!</hi> when he never meant it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:33"/>Many more Diſſentions, and Diviſions amongſt Papiſts might be brought to light: as well as many rediculous abſurdities, errors, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and damnable Doctrines, or Doctrines of Devils: for what elſe is burning the Bible, when printed in the vulgar Tongue of any Nation, and not only that, but all that read it, as Popes have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: and to have all things done in ſtrange Tongues, contrary to the Scriptures. 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 14, 15, 16, 17, 19 2 Tim.</hi> 4. 3, 4.</p>
               <p>The Pope excommunicates all Lay perſons, though never ſo well Learned, that reaſoned in matters of his Faith.</p>
               <p>Again. What an abſurd thing is it, to hear a Prieſt pronounce an Abſolution, which neither the penitent, nor himſelf, underſtands oft times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vid. 6. decret. 1. 5. cap. quicunque.</hi> And all their Church Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, Homilies, and Sermons too for the moſt part are in Latine! Which yet they term an expoſition of the Scripture. What a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous thing is it, to ſee the ignorant vulgar people (Commanded to) hear the Goſpel read in Latine, and withal to behold them earneſtly liſtening with their Ears, leaſt any one word ſhould not be beard, though impoſſible to be underſtood: for which, any man well in his wits would ſuppoſe them all to be Mad.</p>
               <p>There are no leſs than an hundred <hi>Sects, Sorts, Degrees</hi> and <hi>Orders of Fryers, Monks, Nuns,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the Church of Rome,</hi> all which have been ſet up and confirmed by divers Popes ſucceſſively. See <hi>Fox. Acts and Monuments</hi> p. 337.</p>
               <p>Now, it is impoſſible that ſuch a prodigious rabblement, or ſuch a numerous <hi>Heterogeneous Herd,</hi> divided and ſubdivided; not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many ſorts and degrees, but alſo into ſo many opinions (as you have heard, and many more beſides) ſhould keep within bounds, if the <hi>Pope,</hi> his <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and the reſt of his <hi>Grand Clergy,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Baſhaws,</hi> together with his <hi>Popiſh Kings, Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, States, Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracy
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f all degrees, did not by their great power and authority keep them in Aw, in preferring ſome; in threatning and moſt ſeverely puniſhing othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, both Laity a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Clergy, even with Death it ſelf;</hi> ſo that none of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dare ſo much as qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtir in the leaſt: No not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sk, Why
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is? Or, Wherefore is that? Such ſlaves are they: For they are not to queſtion any falſe Doctrines of the Popes: For his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anon Law forbids them in theſe Words. <hi>Non ſpectat ad ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>terminar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, aut examinare quia poſſit papa, aut quid non poſſit, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rere vel non, qui Sacrilegium eſt desputare de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia papae.</hi> It belongeth not to the Popes Vaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls (viz. <hi>Catholicks</hi>)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36213:33"/> to determine, or examen, what the Pope may do, or what he may not do, for his Law (mark) hath made it Sacriledge to diſpute his power. And thoſe that dare do it, muſt look for no leſs puniſhment than Fire and Faggot.</p>
               <p>O then! What a Heavenly happineſs, and bleſſed Liberty Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants enjoy, could they but ſee it, and knew how to uſe it. And what a miſerable ſlavery it is to be a Papiſt? Let any man of reaſon Judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <argument>
                  <p>Having thus given an Account of ſome of the grand Diviſions and Differences amongſt the Papists, and their Clergy. Give me leave alſo to ſhew you most of the principal differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Papiſts and Proteſtants. Which I recommend to ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, too many of them being very apt to be ſeduced and conſequently, deſtroy'd in their Souls; for lack of true knowledge, <hi>whereof God himſelf complains,</hi> Hoſ. 4
1. 6.</p>
                  <p>And I think it may be affirmed with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Featly, That there is no poſſitive Article of our faith, which the Papiſts or the moſt Learned amongſt them, do not hold and Believe for Truth and Catholick.</hi> So that we are upon ſure ground, even by their own Confeſſion. <hi>Vid. Featly Cont. Roffen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>For inſtance.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God. So do the Papiſts. <hi>But they add thereto the</hi> Apocrypha,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We believe the Originals of the Old and New Teſtaments in <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> to be Authentical, and of undoubted Authority: The Papiſts (I ſuppoſe) believe the ſame. But they add, <hi>That the vulgar</hi> Latine <hi>Tranſlation is Authentical alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We believe the Written Word of God to be the ground of Faith, ſo ſay they, but add thereto the <hi>unwritten Word, of mens Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions. Mat. 15. 3. Coloſ.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We believe that Chriſt is the Head of his Church: So do they, <hi>but add to him a viſible Head, the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. We believe there are two places for the departed, Heaven and Hell: They believe ſo too, but add other places more, as
<hi>Purgatory, Limbus patrum,</hi> and <hi>Limbus Infantum, all three in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:36213:34"/>6. We believe that God is to be Worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth: So ſay they too; but add, <hi>That he may be Analogically, and relatively Worſhipped by Images,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We believe that we ought to call upon God: They believe ſo too; but add, <hi>That they may call upon Saints too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. We believe that Chriſt is our Mediator both of Redemption and Interceſſion: They believe the ſame; but add to him
<hi>Angels and Saints: upon whoſe interceſſion and merits they in part rely; and ſo make to themſelves fellow ſaviours with Christ.</hi> Whereas the Scripture ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>That he is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt, that come to God by him, ſeeing He ever liveth to make interceſſion for them.</hi> Heb. 7. 25.</p>
               <p n="9">9. We believe that the Saints in Heaven bear moſt ardent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the Saints on Earth: and pray in general, for the Church Militant: The Papiſts believe ſo too; but add, <hi>That they have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of our particular wants and neceſſities, and pray to God in ſpecial for us,</hi> which we deny.</p>
               <p n="10">10. We believe that Chriſt hath inſtituted two Sacraments in his Church, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm, and the Euchariſt: they believe ſo too; but add to theſe five other of their own inventions: viz.
<hi>Matrimony, Penance, Ordination, Confirmation</hi> and <hi>extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. We believe that Grace is annexed to the Sacrament, in ſuch ſort, that all thoſe who worthily receive them, participate alſo of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Grace: they ſay ſo too; but add, <hi>That the Sacraments confer this Grace,</hi> ex opere operato, <hi>and that God is tyed to them.</hi> So that, by this Doctrine, Children dying without Baptiſm, are neceſſarily Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="12">12. We believe that the intention of the Miniſter is requiſite to the right adminiſtration of the Sacrament: they believe ſo too; but add, <hi>That the effect of the Sacrament dependeth upon the intention of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Priest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. We believe that in the Euchariſt, the worthy communicant really partaketh of Chriſts Body: they believe ſo too; but add,
<hi>That Chriſt is Really and Carnally received under certain accidents, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being Tranſubstantiated.</hi> Which is an Impoſſibility, therefore a mear Nullity.</p>
               <p n="14">14. We believe that we are Juſtified and Saved by the Merits and paſſion of Chriſt; they ſay ſo too; but add, <hi>Their own Merits and Satisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 We believe that we ought to pray for all the Members of Chriſt his Church Militant on Earth: they believe the ſame; but add,
<hi>That we may, and ought to pray for the Dead alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:34"/>16. We believe, and receive the Three Creeds, <hi>viz. The Apoſtles Creed; The Nicene; and that of Athanaſius:</hi> They believe them alſo; but add <hi>A Fourth Creed,</hi> The XII new Articles coined by the Pope, and annexed to the Council of
<hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By theſe you may ſee, how that</hi> Human Additions, Traditions <hi>and</hi> Inventions, <hi>has ſtrangely Marr'd and Defac'd the</hi> Worſhip of God, <hi>whom they must be teaching, and still putting the Holy Ghoſt to School. However, Let the Reader obſerve and ſee, How the Articles of our Belief are drawn out of their own Confeſſion.</hi> That which we, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, hold for Matter of Faith neceſſary to Salvation, the Papiſts hold as well as we: And therefore Ours is the true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Catholick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; <hi>Whereas, Their Superstitious Additions to the Catholick Faith, were never entertained or owned, neither by all Christians in any Age, nor by any Chriſtians in all Ages. Neither are all the Papists in the World able to prove any one point of their</hi> Tridentine Faith
<hi>(wherein they differ from us) to be Catholick. See</hi> Featly
<hi>againſt</hi> Fiſher.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now, as you have had a View of ſome of their Popiſh</hi> Deluſions <hi>whereby they delude and</hi> abuſe <hi>the common People, rendring them more ſenſeleſs than Bruites, &amp;c. And alſo a brief Account of ſome of the principal Diviſions and Differences amongſt the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; With thoſe between Papiſts and Proteſtants: So, let me inform the ignorant (for to them I chiefly direct my Diſcourſe) wherein the</hi> Proteſtants differ: <hi>For, '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is high time we underſtand one another, and as one man oppoſe the Papiſts, thoſe Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of God and good men, if their infernal Impudence and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould ſet them upon us. Proteſtants, I ſay, For I understand there are ſome among us that reject and diſown that Term or Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or at leaſt, care not for it: Therefore I ſhall here omit them; and only ſet down ſuch as call or own themſelves Protestants: And, they are eſpecially theſe Four, viz.</hi> The Epiſcopiſt. The Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. The Independent, <hi>and</hi> The Baptiſts, <hi>one ſort of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WELL then, Wherein differ the firſt, from the Three laſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> In Rites and Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>Wherein differ the Second and Third?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:35"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In Diſcipline only.</p>
               <p>Wherein differ the Fourth from the Third?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In Time only: And from the Second, in Time and Diſcipline. So, their main Diſſentions conſiſt in Circumſtancials, not Subſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: which always may be matter of great Comfort to Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Now, If any Proteſtant be not pleas'd with this ſhort Account, let give a better. For my own part, I underſtand not of any Difference amongſt them, in any Fundamental Points of Religion: as you ſee there is among the Papiſts, for all their vain Boaſting of ſo much Unity. And, who would fain, eſpecially at this day, Set us together by the Eares, and then laugh at us: And for this end, have their Agents and Proſelytes continually among us, or, at leaſt to ſtir us up to Preach, write, and rail againſt each other. And herein (with grief I ſpeak it) they have prevail'd with too many, even lately: as, I fear they may ſtill, with hot ſpirited prejudicated perſons (and perhaps ſome of them here omitted) for that is it our Common Enemy, the Papiſts, would have, and whereat they greatly rejoyce and glory in: whilſt in the mean time, they plot, and really deſign the Deſtruction of us all: which, with them is not only Lawful, but Meritorious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>SEEing the Papiſts cannot down Diſpute</l>
                  <l>CHRIST'S Kingdom, nor the Proteſtants refute,</l>
                  <l>By all their Arguments, both old and new,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe (though ſilly ones) are not a few:</l>
                  <l>Therefore, ſeek otherwiſe, them to annoy,</l>
                  <l>And (if they can) them with the Sword deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>Now, Juſtice <hi>Arnold</hi> they aſſaulted have,</l>
                  <l>As well as <hi>Godfrey:</hi> ſtill more blood they Crave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Note well, that <hi>Godfrey, God's Peace</hi> ſignifies</l>
                  <l>(Whom to their Luſt they made a Sacrifice.)</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Arnold, Honest,</hi> as he is indeed,</l>
                  <l>Sith for his Honeſty they made him bleed.</l>
                  <l>Theſe, cowardly and ſneakingly did they</l>
                  <l>Aſſaſſinate, where no man could them ſpy.</l>
                  <l>They dare not fight till they are three to one,</l>
                  <l>Which unto me and many more is known.</l>
                  <l>Prodigious Projects, ominous and black</l>
                  <l>Are framing ſtill to bring us all to wrack.</l>
                  <l>Preponderated PLOTS and Treacheries</l>
                  <l>Are now conſpicuous unto our eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:36213:35"/>Our <hi>Horizon</hi> they fain would culminate,</l>
                  <l>And with <hi>Narcotick</hi> fumes contaminate</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Britain</hi> once again (now too ſecure)</l>
                  <l>Where, many Sparks they have brought to their Iure:</l>
                  <l>Rude Wretches (wherewith <hi>London</hi> doth abound)</l>
                  <l>Will ſoon turn Papiſts, if the Pope get ground.</l>
                  <l>Atheiſts and Semi-Papiſts, young and old</l>
                  <l>Spring daily, yea, grow very high and bold,</l>
                  <l>While Proteſtants mind nothing but their pelf,</l>
                  <l>Not minding publick, no, but private ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are too narrow ſpirited, alſo,</l>
                  <l>Too daſterdly into the field to go</l>
                  <l>And fight the Papiſts: Were we all like theſe,</l>
                  <l>The Pope might maſter <hi>England</hi> when he pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>But there are others of a nobler mind</l>
                  <l>That are reſolv'd (as <hi>Jeſuites</hi> ye ſhall find)</l>
                  <l>To ſacrifice their, Lives and whole Eſtates,</l>
                  <l>(And many of them too are prime Magnates)</l>
                  <l>'Ere Popery ſhall have the upper hand,</l>
                  <l>Or once be tollerated in the Land.</l>
                  <l>But all our Truſt is only in the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Thereto incourag'd from his ſacred Word.</l>
                  <l>What fearfull Storms and Tempeſts of Sedition, &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>Have Papiſts rais'd againſt the true Religion?</l>
                  <l>Who can the number of their Projects tell?</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Hurricanoes</hi> have riſe out of Hell,</l>
                  <l>To blow the Goſpell out of <hi>Britanny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in its room ſet up <hi>IDOLATRY?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> their <hi>Pericranions</hi> crack</l>
                  <l>How to ſeduce by any crafty knack:</l>
                  <l>A ſect impulſed by Infernal Hate,</l>
                  <l>Witty in <hi>Vengeance</hi> and things deſperate:</l>
                  <l>Men may, but GOD out-witted cannot be,</l>
                  <l>Tis well for Saints there's ſuch a GOD as He.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> all, he can confound,</l>
                  <l>And beat their grand <hi>Partakers</hi> to the ground;</l>
                  <l>Yea, He can frown them all to HELL, and make</l>
                  <l>Great KINGS and PRINCES at his power quake:</l>
                  <l>What can ye do, O Papiſts, if our GOD</l>
                  <l>Forgive our SINS! or ſend another <hi>Rod,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:36213:36"/>Not You, to ſcourge us? We had rather be</l>
                  <l>Chaſtiz'd by <hi>Turks</hi> than ſuch fell <hi>Fiends</hi> as ye.</l>
                  <l>But if it be decreed, That we muſt fall</l>
                  <l>Into your hands; <hi>Cannot the Lord of all</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Earth</hi> remove from us ſo great a Peſt,</l>
                  <l>And US reſtore to <hi>Liberty</hi> and Reſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rome, Rome! <hi>Our God is a Conſuming Fire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Look to thy ſelf, Thou canſt not long reſpire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For thou art Stubble, therefore thou muſt burn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>GOD, in due time will Thee to Aſhes turn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Out of which ſhall no</hi> Phoenix <hi>riſe, as did</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From</hi> London'<hi>s Aſhes; no, it is forbid.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O, STRICTINELLA! thou art rotten hay,</l>
                  <l>And all thy Aſſes, now begin to bray:</l>
                  <l>There's none but <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Desperadoes</hi> will</l>
                  <l>The curs'd Commands of thy
<note n="*" place="margin">Pope</note> 
                     <hi>Nero</hi> fulfil:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> go together go,</l>
                  <l>For ye are both alike: and ſuch a Foe</l>
                  <l>I'd rather fight than any: for the Devil</l>
                  <l>Cannot exceed them both in any <hi>Evill.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They've made themſelves moſt hateful to the world,</l>
                  <l>Which they have oft into Confuſion hurld:</l>
                  <l>Their Works of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> ſhall be brought to
<hi>Light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More <hi>Colemans,</hi> in due time will come in ſight:</l>
                  <l>More Foxes, and more <hi>Guido Fauxes</hi> too</l>
                  <l>With their dark <hi>Lanthorns</hi> (ſet on work by you)</l>
                  <l>Will be diſcovered 'ere long, we hope,</l>
                  <l>And to receive their juſt Reward—A Rope.</l>
                  <l>Yet, if the Pope but ſaint them, all is well,</l>
                  <l>Though many of his Saintlings burn in hell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rogues, Traytors, Cut-throats, ruffians, ſtrumpets</hi> have</l>
                  <l>Been ſainted by his Holineſs: O brave!</l>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Coleman,</hi> and Saint <hi>Whitebread</hi> (for ſo you</l>
                  <l>Blind Papiſts ſtile them) nay then, Saint <hi>Judas</hi> too:</l>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Satan</hi> alſo, for, he's on your ſide,</l>
                  <l>And your chief Friend, it cannot be deny'd,</l>
                  <l>What profits ſuch a glorious Appellation,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> judge them to Condemnation?</l>
                  <l>Ore of your Saints, when dead three daies he lay,</l>
                  <l>With gaſtly looks, theſe fearful words did ſay:</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:36213:36"/>
                  <l>1. <hi>Ad judicium vocatus ſum!</hi> the firſt day.</l>
                  <l>2. <hi>Judicatus ſum!</hi> the ſecond day.</l>
                  <l>3. <hi>Condemnatus ſum!</hi> the third day: and then they buried him.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>I can take my Oath, that I have heard this verified by many Prieſts, and other Papiſts, at ſeveral times.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>All is not Gold that gliſtereth: no, no,</l>
                  <l>For none are Saints, but whom God maketh ſo:</l>
                  <l>(Some Proteſtants are Saints of their own making,</l>
                  <l>So ruine themſelves through their own miſtaking:)</l>
                  <l>Phanaticiſm, high-Towr'ing Speculation</l>
                  <l>Or Jeſuitiſm, ſome think, is true Salvation.</l>
                  <l>The
<note n="*" place="margin">See the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the
<hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boniſts</hi> in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, call'd, <hi>A Truth known to few, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Sorbonne</hi> Cenſures of their Propoſitions;</l>
                  <l>Shew they are Atheists; and mere Politicians.</l>
                  <l>The Jeſuites, that Phariſaical Tribe,</l>
                  <l>No bounds to their blood-thirſty Wills preſcribe:</l>
                  <l>They, they would rule the Roſte in every place,</l>
                  <l>And meddle in every matter, thing and caſe:</l>
                  <l>They take upon them (and that more of late,)</l>
                  <l>To Tutor Princes in Affairs of State:</l>
                  <l>Impoſing on the World their addle Theams,</l>
                  <l>Driving wild Fancy's into hot Extreams</l>
                  <l>Of dire Diſſention, that they might thereby</l>
                  <l>Confound, amaze, aſtoniſh, ſtupify,</l>
                  <l>Distract, diſturb, diſſettle, and divide,</l>
                  <l>Exciting men to blood, on every ſide.</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbounded in their Malice to all thoſe</l>
                  <l>That cannot with their Machinations cloſe:</l>
                  <l>Damn'd Wretches, what, will nothing ſerve your turn,</l>
                  <l>But Towns and Cities through meere Malice burn?</l>
                  <l>Will nothing ſatisfy your
<note n="*" place="margin">Pope</note> 
                     <hi>Hildebrand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But the Deſtruction af a Christian Land?</l>
                  <l>What strange <hi>Cataſtrophe's?</hi> what woful things</l>
                  <l>Have they brought upon Kingdoms, States and Kings.</l>
                  <l>Setting them all-together by the Ears,</l>
                  <l>Filling the world with Terrors, Frights, and Fears.</l>
                  <l>What Fools have been the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and
<hi>Spain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To kiſs their Gouty Toes, and hold their Train,</l>
                  <l>And ſtirrups too! walking by their Horſe-ſide,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt they did ſwell with Arrogance and Pride?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36213:37"/>
                  <head>O, Generation of Vipers, when</head>
                  <l>Will ye ceaſe to be Devils, and act like men?</l>
                  <l>When will ye ceaſe to prey upon your kind?</l>
                  <l>Which Cruelty, in Wolves, ye cannot find:</l>
                  <l>Your Mines, and Countermines, are dug as deep</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Hell,</hi> with which, ye Correspondence keep:</l>
                  <l>Ye <hi>Mine</hi> for Blood, and <hi>undermine</hi> to bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p Parliaments for we have found it ſo:</l>
                  <l>Witneſs that noted fift day of <hi>November.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1605.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, without horrour, we cannot remember.</l>
                  <l>The Maſſacres in <hi>France,</hi> poor
<hi>Switzerland,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bohemia, Piedmond, Ireland, Pomerland,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1588"/>
                     <hi>Hungaria the</hi> Spaniſh
<hi>Inquiſition,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> have made away a Million!<note place="margin">Jeſuits by Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation have deni'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Chriſtians.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet do the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and all the Rout</l>
                  <l>Of Papiſts, impudently face it out,</l>
                  <l>That there were no ſuch things! No all are Lies,</l>
                  <l>Which you (ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y) on purpoſe did devize!</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Powder-Plot</hi> was forge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> too! (They Cry)</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Faux, (&amp;c.)</hi> confest it, and therefore did dy.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>As did Sir</hi> Edw. Digby, R. Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, T. Winter, A. Rookwood, R. Keys, J. Grant T. Bates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay! they deny the PLOT diſcovered, now,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Otes</hi> and <hi>Bodloe!</hi> Yea, they ſwear and vow,</l>
                  <l>Such things were n'ere intended! Thus, you ſee,</l>
                  <l>What impudent, what canting KOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES they be?</l>
                  <l>Hoping thereby to blear the eyes of ſome,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt they ſhould ſee the Villanies of ROME:</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſurely, none but Reprobates will heed</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Cannibals</hi> as love on Saints to feed,</l>
                  <l>And ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d of Innocents, becauſe</l>
                  <l>They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſubſcribe to their Prodigious Laws.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ye <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> O, ye State-Mountebanks!</l>
                  <l>That with your Projects, and Hell-hatchd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pranks</l>
                  <l>Do ſo much M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſchief, till ye are pull'd down,</l>
                  <l>No Chriſtian Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce can ſafely ware a Crown:</l>
                  <l>Sure, ye muſt needs be of the Race of <hi>Cain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For that your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reateſt Care is how to Stain</l>
                  <l>The Earth with Brooks of Blood of ſuch as are</l>
                  <l>True <hi>Abels,</hi> or watch how, them, to enſnare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36213:37"/>
                  <l>From JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, ye, your ſelves denominate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jeſuites!</hi> and yet his Goſpel-Truths ye hate!</l>
                  <l>And all
<note n="*" place="margin">Quos time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, odimus.</note> true Gospellers: Nay, do not ye</l>
                  <l>Make him the Spring of all your Villany!</l>
                  <l>Lord God! Who can their Blaſphemies expreſs,</l>
                  <l>A Patron unto all your Wickedneſs!</l>
                  <l>Without Astoniſhment and Indignation!</l>
                  <l>Was e're ſuch Devils on Earth ſince the Creation!</l>
                  <l>A JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITE, <hi>(i. e.) à Jeſu ite,</hi> Go</l>
                  <l>From Jeſus: but he never own'd them, no:</l>
                  <l>Yet, in his Name all evils they begin,</l>
                  <l>Hoping thereby more Proſelytes to win.</l>
                  <l>Therefore it may be ſaid of their blind BAALAM,</l>
                  <l>☞ <hi>In nomine Domini, incipit omne Malum!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And they alſo, which, in a ſence, is true;</l>
                  <l>But they, and all their <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> Crew</l>
                  <l>Will have the blaſting <hi>Benediction</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of their Arch <hi>Flamin</hi> e're they fall upon</l>
                  <l>The Proteſtants, which having got, they then,</l>
                  <l>Believe themſelves to be more than men,</l>
                  <l>As they're, indeed in a right ſence, for why?</l>
                  <l>All others they exceed in Cruelty.</l>
                  <l>GOD bleſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, from the bleſſing of the POPE,</l>
                  <l>For in GOD's bleſſing is our Help and Hope.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We plainly ſee it is thy Drift and Aim,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to enthrall, <hi>O Cuſhan-riſhathaim!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But art thou ſure to carry't? Canſt thou tell</l>
                  <l>What God will do? Canſt bear away the Bell</l>
                  <l>By thine own Power, force and Policy?</l>
                  <l>Yes, thou thinkſt: yet who knows but the moſt HIGH</l>
                  <l>At laſt may ſmile on us, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s ſucceed?</l>
                  <l>And all thy <hi>Colemans</hi> from amongſt us weed,</l>
                  <l>And make us, yet, to ſee more <hi>Halcion</hi> daies:</l>
                  <l>If ſo, thy Jeſuites cannot wear the Bayes.</l>
                  <l>Therefore conſider, Look before you Leap,</l>
                  <l>Lest Wrath and Vengeance on thy ſelf thou heap.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:36213:38"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reader, That thou mayſt not have the leaſt Thought of complying with theſe Curſed Enemies of our dear LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, and the Simple Purity of his Worſhip, No, though to ſave thy life: for having here obſerved how thou art to be deluded and abuſed in thy Temporal Concerns, and much more in thy Eternal, by ignorant, ſottiſh Priests, &amp;c. I ſhall add a dreadful Example of Gods Judgment upon a parcel of Wretches who turn'd in a moment from being Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to be Papiſts: being a Seaſonable Warning to Apostatizing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; verifying in the very Letter thoſe Words of our Saviour, which contain in them a Curſe, and a Bleſſing,</hi> viz. Whoſoever will ſave his Life ſhall looſe it: and whoſoever will looſe his Life for my ſake, ſhall find it, <hi>Mat.
16. 25. as, in the following Story is made out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW are the Daies, doubtleſs, whereof Chriſt and his Apoſtles forewarn'd us; <hi>That there ſhould be a departing or falling away from the Faith:</hi> (1 Tim. 4. 1. 2 Pet. 3. 3. Jude 18.) <hi>and that becauſe of Iniquities abounding, the love of many ſhould wax cold,</hi> Matt. 24. 12. Cold for Chriſt and the true Chriſtian Religion; Nay,
<hi>They ſhall even deny Chriſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 1. 2 Tim. 2. 12. And theſe things, with many more are come to paſs at this very day.</p>
               <p>And this hath proceeded from the curſed deſign of the JESUITES, and the reſt of the Romiſh Faction, who debauch many great Ones, and, they, by their wicked Example (which almoſt carries the force of a Command with it) the whole Comonaley, (by deluding them with pretences of Venial ſins, and Pardons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) For is not Whoring, Swar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drunkning, Lying, Aequivocating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> become as a mighty Stream overflowing the whole Land, thereby fitting us for ſome worſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if the Plague, the Fire, and other Puniſhments we have had, do no good upon us. Therefore be ſteadfaſt: How dreadful is it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and what a ſure Token of approaching Judgment is it, to ſee</p>
               <p>I. Many <hi>quandam</hi> zealous Proteſtants, grown of late ſo cold, (col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſince the PLOT than before) ſo narrow ſpirited and baſely ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, (thinking 'tis a great piece of diſcretion, and that they ſhew an emphatical piece of Wiſdom) That when Diſcourſe is raiſed in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, concerning POPERY, they will either ſhift it off with a Drool, force ſome other Diſcourſe, or ſneak away, in hopes to ſave their Bakon, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:36213:38"/> (<hi>cujus contrarium verum eſt,</hi>) ſo that, really, they are aſham'd, or half afraid to own themſelves Proteſtants: Shewing not ſo mch zeal for the true Worſhip of the true God, as a
<hi>Turk</hi> does for <hi>Mahomets,</hi> or a <hi>Heathen</hi> for his
<hi>Idol:</hi> hereby declaring that they have ſat under a dead Miniſtry, of whom God hath ſaid, <hi>They ſhall not profit the People.</hi> Thoſe that never felt the Power of God, under an Ordinance, in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from all Sin, and ſhewing them the deſperateneſs of their Condition without Chriſt, a holy Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will turn to any, the worſt of prevailing Religions, eſpecially to that which tolerlates Sin, as Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry do's: nay, makes it meritorious, as murdering Kings, burning Cities, &amp;c!</p>
               <p>II. Others are ſo puſillanimous, ſo dirty, and daſtardly; That they dare not own the Truth, when they hear it traduced and impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by men popiſhly affected: when e'n the Spirit of God and their own Conſciences prompt them to ſpeak: as if they were aſham'd of Chriſt, (See <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 38.) and with <hi>Spira,</hi> deſperately quench and reſiſt the Motions of the Holy Ghoſt: and if any put them to it by Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they'l anſwer with an Equivocation, or an <hi>Italian</hi> ſhrug: Know, they that dare not Speak for Chriſt, will hardly either Do or Suffer for him; Theſe are light Wheat, that will ſoon be blown aſide, if the Wind riſes a little: eſpecially, if <hi>Euroclydon</hi> blow hard.</p>
               <p>III. There is alſo another ſort, who, tho they will talk pretty freely concerning the PLOT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet their words are ſo cunningly and artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially placed, as if they were coin'd on purpoſe: Yea their Expreſſions are many times ſo ambiguous, and ſavoring of the JESUITS can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Querks, that the wiſeſt Man alive can hardly tell what to make of them: and all theſe three aim at the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> hoping, by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Indifferency, and Neutrality, to find favour of the Papiſts, if they ſhould get uppermoſt; which is the greateſt Folly imaginable: as I could evince by many woful Examples, in the Rebellion, in
<hi>Ireland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> where they were moſt egregiouſly perfidious, promiting the Proteſtants quarter, but in ſtead thereof murdered them in cold Blood: And this one Relation, ſhall ſerve in ſtead of many, whereby you may ſee, if you will, what you are to expect when they have the Sword,
<hi>&amp;c. Take it faithfully as I receiv'd it from Captain</hi> Edward Leventhorp, <hi>and others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>DUring the late Wars in <hi>Ireland,</hi> A Caſtle well mann'd with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Proteſtants, being ſuddenly and ſtraightly beſieged by the Enemy, in ſo much, that in few daies, they were reduced to ſo great Extremity, that they muſt of neceſſity either ſtarve, or yield to the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36213:39"/> Mercy of the mercileſs and implacable Papiſts (whoſe
<hi>tender Mercies are Cruelty;</hi> as all along the <hi>Maryan</hi> Dayes, the Troubles in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion hath been proved.)</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Say you ſo? Quoth the Popiſh Commander! But what, I pray, Do'nt you think the others, that ſeparated from you, good
<hi>Catholicks?</hi> No, (ſaid the ſtedfaſt Soldiers) becauſe they never own'd themſelves as ſuch till now, and they do it for fear of Death.</p>
               <p>I verily believe it (ſaid the Commander) for I thought as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Then turning to the reſt of his Officers and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uldiers, he ſaid, Them yonder, meaning thoſe that ſeparated, are but Counterfeit <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> and the Rogues do it only to ſave their LIVES, and to abuſe us, for they will run away the next Opportunity: <hi>Therefore, by GOD, they ſhall dy every man of them, and the other for ſtanding ſo bravely to their Principles ſhall live; and whom I would ſooner truſt, upon any occaſion, than the other, or any ſuch Time-ſerving Raſcals, as they are!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, he put all the Revolters to the Sword, any ſaved the other for their brave Reſolution: and not only ſo, but ſent them with a ſafe Conduct to the next Engliſh Garriſon, having as many of his own ſent in Exchange<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that had been Priſoners. By this noble Act, the ſaid Commander won great Applauſe amongſt the Engliſh.</p>
               <p>Now, conſider this, all ye that think to ſave your Lives and Eſtates by temporiſing and baſely antedating your Religion, or dirtily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with, and fawning upon every baſe pitiful (the moſt of them are no better) Papiſt before hand, as if ye would fore-ſpeak Friendſhip, as I am too ſure many do. And poſſibly, you that are next to, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but one little ſtep from them, may find ſome favour, for a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, from them, till you and them, if they can by any idle fooliſh pretence get you to aſſiſt them againſt ſuch as are more zealous againſt their Idolatries: But, when their work is ſo far done, then they will more eaſily cut you off too, for the leaſt ſtep of Reformation ſince <hi>Qu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:36213:40"/> Maries</hi> daies, their Soul bates, even as the pureſt worſhip. For I can liken them to no better a Crew than Rogues and Thieves that live in an honeſt place; who will carry it very fairly among the Neighbourhood, to have ſome bodies good word at a pinch: ſo they, make to ſome one party to ſhelter under them: and then, only <hi>Polyphemus</hi>'s Courteſy will be yours, that is, to dy laſt, when you have ſeen the Throats of others cut, your own turn comes next.</p>
               <p>There are Seven ſorts that above all others are moſt likely to turn Apoſtates, <hi>viz.</hi> The Covetous, the Ambitious, the Self-lovers, the Over-nice, the Forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſts, the Ignorant and the Fearful. See <hi>Rev. 21. 8. Mat. 10.
33. Mark. 13. 13. Rev. 2. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25. 1 Cor. 16. 13. Phil. 4. 1. 1. Cr.</hi>
10. 12.</p>
               <p>Theſe 7 include the firſt three abovenamed; and are wrapt up in the word HYPOCRITE; and amongſt them, there are divers great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors even of all ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rts, who (as well as the looſe, ignorant, debauch'd, prophane Proteſtants) for fear or favour, may joyn with the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſincere Proteſtants; as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> joyned with Papiſts againſt the <hi>Calveniſts, An.</hi> 1567. and about the 10 year of Q.
<hi>Eliz.</hi> eſpecially when alluted thereto by the curious Arts of Jeſuites and their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, the Philtring Baites of Profit and Preferment: Seconded by the luſty (tho ſeigned) Promiſes of ſome principal Papiſts and their Agents. But God can (and perhaps will) bring it ſo to paſs, That ſuch revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wrethes, may be ſerved as they above mention'd: or, if not ſo, yet they cannot eſcape Vengeance: for I am confident they will periſh by one means or other, perchance by the hands of true Proteſtants: And, for my own part, I do profeſs, (if God will make uſe of the Arm of Fleſh, in our defence) I would ſooner give quarter to
<hi>French</hi> or any other outlandiſh-Papiſt, than any Engliſh Apoſtate whatſoever (Laity or Clergy) that ſhould joyn in Arms with them, or our domeſtick or home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Papiſts againſt the Proteſtants Cauſe.</p>
               <p>And I write this with an heart that never yet feared the greateſt or the proudeſt Papiſt in the World: who have been at the routing of ſuch, almoſt an hundred times, in my junior daies: and therefore, I think, I ſhould know the better how to deal with them now; if they will needs force us to it, by falling upon us firſt: for till then we will not ſtir one foot: Let them otherwiſe provoke us never ſo much, as they have done very often, and do daily: beſides burning of <hi>London, Southwark, &amp;c.</hi> But as crafty Fowlers as they are, they ſhall not catch old Birds in the Chaff ☞ <hi>Be ſteadfaſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.
58.—<hi>ſtand faſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 13. For, In all Gods Armory, there's no defence for the Back, the Runagade <pb facs="tcp:36213:40"/> or Apoſtate muſt everlaſtingly periſh. O Apoſtate, bethink thy ſelf betimes!</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>True Proteſtants will rather chuſe to dy,</l>
                  <l>Than Chriſt, or their Religion deny:</l>
                  <l>And bravely perſevere, come, what will come,</l>
                  <l>But Hypocrites will how the Knee to Rome,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n theſe 7 Monſters, which I nam'd before,</l>
                  <l>Would Popery, if it were up, adore.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, Let us, and all that think they ſtand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leſt we fall, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12.) as they may, without Divine Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: Self-Confidence being a moſt dangerous Rock on which many have ſplit, even in this preſent Age: Remember the Apoſtle
<hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtate <hi>Pendleton,</hi> in the Book of Martyrs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Errata.</hi> Page 6. l. 6. r. Deluſions: <hi>p.</hi> 32. l.
16. <hi>after</hi> Pope, <hi>add</hi> forbad them. p. 34. l. 16. <hi>r.</hi> Angles. p. 40. l. 15. <hi>r.</hi> Connivium. p. 50. l. 7. <hi>r.</hi> him give. p. 53. <hi>r. the 14 &amp; 15 lines before the</hi> 12 &amp; 13. p. 55.
<hi>read line 6 before line</hi> 5.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>BOoks and ſingle ſheets Printed and ſold by</hi> Tho. Dawks, <hi>in Blackfryers, and by</hi> La Curtiſs <hi>in Goat Court on Ludgate-hill, where may alwayes be had,</hi> 1. Godfreys Murder <hi>made viſible, and the Papists Cruelty therein. 2. A Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Popery, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing When, and Who brought in their idle, fooliſh F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perys. 3. The only Hiſtorical Plot Cards, with a Book, illuſtrating the PLOT, greatly ſatisfying the Protestant Reader. 4. The Beggars Petition to</hi> H. S. <hi>ſhewing Reaſons enough why he threw Popery off, and, we are not to be befoold into it. 5. The 3 Prime Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers, their Pictures, with Verſes ſhewing their Reaſons why they diſcovered this Helliſh Popiſh Plot. 6. Romes Hunting-Match for 3 Kingdoms.</hi> 7. England's <hi>Calamity foreſhown, from the growth of Popery, in</hi> Germanys <hi>Miſery. 8. A Seaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Caution to Apostatizing Protestants; or Gods eminent Judgment upon Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants that turn'd Papiſts to ſave their Lives, but periſhed. 8. The</hi> Reſurrection <hi>proved in a Relation of what hapned to Mris</hi> Ann Atherton, <hi>who lay 7 dayes in a Trance, declared in an aſtoniſhing Speech when ſhe came to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9 <hi>A great Truth,</hi> The Jeſuit a down-right Compleat Atheiſt, <hi>proved ſuch, and condemn'd for ſuch, by the</hi> Famous Faculty of Sorbonne (<hi>well known to be the beſt Divines of all the Catholick Party; and by the</hi> French Biſhops) &amp; Pope <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander 7. Shewing how they make a Mock at Sin, deny God, and overthrow all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Their Deſign being to Debauch Mankind, wherein they, as a Judgment from God upon us, have ſucceeded pretty well, but ſpeedy Judgment attends its Promoters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10 <hi>Famous Maſter</hi> Rich's <hi>Abſence ſupply'd by a KEY to his</hi> Sort-hand-TABLE, <hi>entituled</hi> The PENS Dexterity,
<hi>Allowed and Approved by both <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities. Fully diſcovering the whole Art to the Meaneſt Capacity, in that Method he Taught his Scholars, with the reſerved Rules in their proper Places: by</hi> T. Dawks, <hi>a</hi> quandam <hi>Scholar of his; the like never publickly diſcovered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; all Books and ſheets relating to this Hand has been Abuſes to the Publick, &amp; the Buyers of them much deceiv'd, for the Table alone was ne'r deſign'd by Mr.</hi> Rich <hi>to teach the whole ART, but to bring Scholars to him: And for the Truth of what I ſay, as well in relation to this K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, as to other ſpurious Books, I refer my ſelf to Mr.</hi> Rich's <hi>Scholars, as fittest Judges, knowing not where elſe to appeal. Alſo I have added ſince it came to my hand (beſides the Key, to diſtinguiſh this from all falſ Tables) Directions concerning the place of Vowels, which he gave me in writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the private Rules. Wherefore, all old Tables without the Key are falſe ones, beware of them. Theſe true ones are ſold by</hi> T. Baſſet, <hi>at the George by S.</hi> Dunſtans, <hi>Church in Fleetstreet: by</hi> Fr. Smith <hi>at the Elephant by the Exchange in Cornhil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11. Magnalia Naturae. <hi>The Philoſophers Stone, Expoſed to publick</hi> Sight <hi>and</hi> Sale. <hi>Being an Account how</hi> Wenceſlaus Seilerus, <hi>at the Emperours Court, in</hi> Vienna, <hi>came by, and made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>way with great quantities thereof. Atteſted by the Emperour himſelf, by Count</hi> Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſtein <hi>his late Reſident here: and by Dr.</hi> Becher <hi>a Commiſſioner for the</hi> Examen <hi>of this particular Affair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12. Dr. <hi>Salmons</hi> Soul of Aſtrology.</p>
            <p>13. <hi>His</hi> Synopſis Medicinae <hi>will ſpeedily be publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36213:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
